<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Refactoring | Karol Galanciak - Ruby on Rails and Ember.js consultant]]></title>
  <link href="https://karolgalanciak.com/blog/categories/refactoring/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://karolgalanciak.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-09-29T15:41:00+02:00</updated>
  <id>https://karolgalanciak.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Karol Galanciak]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Refactoring Tips: Trade Conditionals For Type Delegation]]></title>
    <link href="https://karolgalanciak.com/blog/2016/01/06/refactoring-tips-trade-conditionals-for-type-delegation/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-06T23:20:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://karolgalanciak.com/blog/2016/01/06/refactoring-tips-trade-conditionals-for-type-delegation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Having some kind of <code>type</code> attribute in your models is a pretty common thing, especially in applications with more complex domain. How do you handle such cases? Is it with multiple conditionals / <code>case</code> statements in every method dealing with the type attribute? If you've been struggling with organizing and maintaing code for such use cases then say hello to your new friend: type delegation.</p>




<!--more-->




<h2>Type attribute - common approach</h2>




<p>Imagine you have some <code>Subscription</code> model with <code>type</code> and <code>charged_at</code> columns. Let's assume that the possible values for <code>type</code> column are <code>daily</code>, <code>weekly</code>, <code>monthly</code> and <code>yearly</code>. Now let's add couple of methods: next charge date, subscription price and maybe eligible discount which is going to depend on the subscription type as well. To make it a bit more complex let's assume that for <code>yearly</code> subscription the user needs to select some kind of <code>bonus</code>. The common approach to this problem would be the following:</p>


<p>``` ruby
class Subscription &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
  validate :bonus_id, presence: true, if: &ndash;> subscription { subscription.eligible_for_bonus? }</p>

<p>  def next_charge_at</p>

<pre><code>charged_at.advance(days: subscription_days)
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def price</p>

<pre><code>base_daily_price * subscription_days - discount
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def discount</p>

<pre><code>case type
when "daily"
  0
when "weekly"
  100
when "monthly"
  500
when "yearly"
  10000
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  private</p>

<p>  def base_daily_price</p>

<pre><code>100
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def subscription_days</p>

<pre><code>case type
when "daily"
  1
when "weekly"
  7
when "monthly"
  30
when "yearly"
  365
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def eligible_for_bonus?</p>

<pre><code>return true if type == "yearly"
false
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>This class is quite short, but already suffers from the conditionals in many places and as the logic grows, the <code>case</code> and <code>if</code> statements are going to be in even more places, which will be a maintenance nightmare. Are there any ways we could make it better?</p>




<p>The simplest one would be probably using a hash instead of <code>case</code> or <code>if</code> statements. Here's one example for <code>discount</code>:</p>


<p>``` ruby
class Subscription &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
  TYPES_DISCOUNTS_MAPPING = {</p>

<pre><code>daily: 0,
weekly: 100,
monthly: 500,
yearly: 10000
</code></pre>

<p>  }.freeze</p>

<p>  def discount</p>

<pre><code>TYPES_DISCOUNTS_MAPPING.fetch(type.to_sym)
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>It looks better than conditionals, but the idea is still the same. It may also grow too complex when you don't return a simple value based on the type, but perform some computations which would mean having lambdas as a return value per type.</p>




<p>For a real change we could introduce more object-oriented techniques. How about polymorphism and delegation? Every type of subscription looks like a separate concept, maybe we could encapsulate logic related to each type in the separate classes implementing the same interface? That way we would reduce the number of conditionals in all possible cases to just one - in the method where we actually return the type class for given subscription type. Let's see how it works in practice:</p>


<p>``` ruby
class Subscription &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
  TYPES_CLASSES_MAPPING = {</p>

<pre><code>daily: DailySubscription,
weekly: WeeklySubscription,
monthly: MonthlySubscription,
yearly: YearlySubscription
</code></pre>

<p>  }.freeze</p>

<p>  validate :bonus_id, presence: true, if: &ndash;> subscription { subscription.eligible_for_bonus? }</p>

<p>  delegate :discount, :subscription_days, :eligible_for_bonus?, to: :type_class</p>

<p>  def next_charge_at</p>

<pre><code>charged_at.advance(days: subscription_days)
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def price</p>

<pre><code>base_daily_price * subscription_days - discount
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  private</p>

<p>  def type_class</p>

<pre><code>TYPES_CLASSES_MAPPING.fetch(type.to_sym).new
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def base_daily_price</p>

<pre><code>100
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  class DailySubscription</p>

<pre><code>def discount
  0
end

def subscription_days
  1
end

def eligible_for_bonus?
  false
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  class WeeklySubscription</p>

<pre><code>def discount
  100
end

def subscription_days
  7
end

def eligible_for_bonus?
  false
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  class MonthlySubscription</p>

<pre><code>def discount
  500
end

def subscription_days
  30
end

def eligible_for_bonus?
  false
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  class YearlySubscription</p>

<pre><code>def discount
  10000
end

def subscription_days
  365
end

def eligible_for_bonus?
  true
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>Now each type is a separate domain concept and it's really simple to extend any logic based on the type: we would just need to add a method to every class without worrying about ugly conditionals and simply delegate the method call to <code>type_object</code> using <code>delegate</code> macro from ActiveSupport.</p>




<p>You may be wondering whether it actually improved design as there's more code and classes. The answer is still yes: the object-orientation is all about interaction between many objects and identifying domain concepts almost always result in larger, but more explicit and easier to maintain codebase.</p>




<h2>Wrapping up</h2>




<p>Type delegation is a simple technique aimed for eliminating conditional logic in different methods that depend on some <code>type</code> attribute and making code much easier to maintain and extend.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Model your domain with composed models]]></title>
    <link href="https://karolgalanciak.com/blog/2015/02/26/model-your-domain-with-composed-models/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-26T09:10:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://karolgalanciak.com/blog/2015/02/26/model-your-domain-with-composed-models</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In many Rails applications the modeling is limited only to creating classes inheritng from <code>ActiveRecord::Base</code> which are 1:1 mapped to database tables. Having AR models like <code>User</code> and <code>Project</code> doesn't tell much about the domain of your application. Well, you can add some domain logic to the models but that way you will easily end up having giant classes with thousands lines of code, so let's just use models for database-related stuff only. Other option would be to create service objects for every usecase. That's a good and clean way, but it's merely the interaction layer between different parts of your application. You may end up easily with all logic encapsulated within service objects that will start looking more like procedural programming rather than proper OOP and not real domain API at all. The good news is that you can easily counteract it: time to use composed models.</p>




<!--more-->




<h2>Definition and examples composed models</h2>




<p>Composed models are classes which emphasize the relation between entities and the interactions between them. In most applications the models have multiple different relations between each other, rarely are they self-contained. So what happens if we take some entities and try to put them in one class?</p>




<p>Imagine you are developing project management application and you've got <code>User</code>, <code>Project</code> and <code>Task</code> models. What are the possible interactions between these models? User can be assigned to many tasks in a given project, so we can both query for the existing tasks and add some new tasks. We would probably query for finished tasks, currently being done and the ones not started. We may also check if user is in given project or can add/remove him/her from the project. In this case, the predominant relation is the one between the <code>user</code> and <code>project</code>, so let's create a class <code>UserWithProject</code>. We will make it a decorator over these two models, so the class will take both <code>user</code> and <code>project</code> to constructor:</p>


<p>``` ruby
class UserWithProject
  attr_reader :user, :project
  private     :user, :project</p>

<p>  def initialize(user, project)</p>

<pre><code>@user = user
@project = project
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>Let's add some actual logic to our composed model: querying for different tasks for related <code>user</code> and <code>project</code>, adding new tasks, checking if user is assigned to the project and maybe leaving the project. </p>


<p>``` ruby
class UserWithProject
  attr_reader :user, :project
  private     :user, :project</p>

<p>  def initialize(user, project)</p>

<pre><code>@user = user
@project = project
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def tasks</p>

<pre><code>@tasks ||= project.tasks.with_assignee(user)
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def pending_tasks</p>

<pre><code>tasks.pending
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def finished_tasks</p>

<pre><code>tasks.finished
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def not_started_tasks</p>

<pre><code>tasks.not_started
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def add_task(task)</p>

<pre><code>task.asignee = user
task.project = project
task.save!
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def assigned_to_project?</p>

<pre><code>project.users.include?(user)
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def leave_project</p>

<pre><code>project.users.destroy(user)
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>Most methods are probably self-explanatory and don't need to be discussed. Now we have an actual domain model which neatly encapsulates interactions between <code>users</code>, <code>projects</code> and <code>tasks</code>. Looks like a real API for application that can be simply (re)used.</p>




<p>One usecase for composed models is about interactions between models. But this patterns also shines when you consider some modifiers of values. By modifier I mean an object that has some kind of influence on values being returned by methods of other object. For example you might be developing an e-commerce app and have <code>Order</code> with <code>total_price</code>. Let's imagine that you need to handle discounts for orders, which as you max expect, are going to decrease <code>total_price</code>. With composed model pattern you could create <code>OrderWithDiscount</code> class. To make it still behave like an <code>Order</code> instance, the class may inherit from <code>SimpleDelegator</code> and all the method calls not implemented by <code>OrderWithDiscount</code> are going to be delegated to <code>Order</code>:</p>


<p>``` ruby
class OrderWithDiscount &lt; SimpleDelegator
  attr_reader :order, :discount
  private     :order, :discount</p>

<p>  def initialize(order, discount)</p>

<pre><code>@order = order
@discount = discount
super(order)
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def total_price</p>

<pre><code># somehow apply the discount.value to order.total_price
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>That way you can still have <code>total_price</code> on Order without adding additional arguments, conditionals etc. for handling discounts and have a separate object for special usecases.</p>




<h2>Extracting existing logic to composed models</h2>




<p>Now that you know how what are the composed models for, you may be wondering how to extract already existing codebase to that pattern. Fortunately, it's easy to tell in many cases if a particular method is a good fit to move. When you have multiple methods in one class taking the same kind of argument(s), that's probably a good idea to think about some changes. Let's use the example with <code>User</code> and <code>Project</code>. If that pattern hadn't been used there we would probably have had some code in <code>Project</code> model looking like this:</p>


<p>``` ruby
class Project &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
  # associations and stuff like that</p>

<p>  def tasks_for_user(user)</p>

<pre><code># some logic
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def pending_tasks_for_user(user)</p>

<pre><code># some logic
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def finished_tasks_for_user(user)</p>

<pre><code># some logic
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def add_task_for_user(task, user)</p>

<pre><code># some logic
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>This class really begs for refactoring ;). Another sign would be having methods where there might be an argument modyfing the value or may not. Using the <code>Order</code> example, there could be a method like:</p>


<p>``` ruby
class Order &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
  def total_price(discount: nil)</p>

<pre><code># somehow calculate the total_price
if discount?
  # apply the discount
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>Doesn't really look great, having separate class makes it much easier to read and understand.</p>




<h2>Wrapping up</h2>




<p>I've shown a pretty cool pattern I've started using recently, which works really great and makes a big difference when looking at the domain logic of the application. I hope you will find it useful.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rails: Useful Patterns]]></title>
    <link href="https://karolgalanciak.com/blog/2014/09/17/rails-useful-patterns/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-17T19:55:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://karolgalanciak.com/blog/2014/09/17/rails-useful-patterns</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There've been a lot of discussions for several months about "The Rails Way" and problems associated with it - huge models with several thousands lines of code and no distinguishable responsibilities (User class which does everything related to users doesn't tell much what the app does), unmaintainable callback hell and no domain objects at all. Fortunately, service objects (or usecases) and other forms of extracting logic from models have become quite mainstream recently. However, it's not always clear how to use them all together without creating huge classes with tens of private methods and too many responsibilities. Here are some strategies you can use to solve these problems.</p>




<!--more-->


<p></p>

<h2>Pass form objects as data aggregates to service objects</h2>




<p>Imagine situation where your usecase involves more than one model, some virtual attributes are needed etc., basically the usecase where form object is necessary (unless you want to have a serious mess in models). Furthermore, you need to implement pretty complex features - besides proper mapping of attributes to models in form objects you want to send some notifications, log an activity and other stuff. How to tackle such a problem? Often I see a code where all custom logic, apart from simple saving data, is put in form objects. That's not really a way to go. Why start from separating responsibilities and end up with form object which does everything? You can easily handle it by passing form objects with populated data to service objects. Take a look at the controller action below:</p>


<p>``` ruby
class UsersController &lt; ApplicationController</p>

<p>  def create</p>

<pre><code>user = User.new
form = User::RegistrationForm.new(user)
registration = User::Registration.new(logger: MyFancyCustomLogger, mailer: User::RegistraionMailer)

if form.validate(params) &amp;&amp; registration.register(form)
  # success path
else
  # failure path
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>end
```</p>

<p>The <code>UsersController</code> is responsible here for control flow, form aggregates and validates data and <code>User::Registration</code> does some domain business logic and assumes it operates on valid data. Looks and feels great, it's easy to test and the responsibilities are clear. I also inject some dependencies in the constructor of <code>User::Registration</code> to make it even more testable and extensible.</p>


<p></p>

<p>The only problem with such an approach is lack of compatibility or difficulties with customization with some gems (like <code>inherited_resources</code>). But gems shouldn't force you to write code in a particular way and it would be probably better to give up on them and enjoy a clean code.</p>




<h2>Create flexible service objects with listeners</h2>




<p>Let's consider previous usecase: registration. Imagine situation where you need three types of user registration: “normal” one like when you enter the page and want to create an account,  registration by admin and registering new users by non-admin within some kind of groups. The core of registration process remains the same in all cases. However, there will be slight differences between the usesaces, eg. there won't be any notification sent to admin when user is being registered by admin. One way would be to create service object for each usecase and encapsulate entire logic within them. But it may lead to code that is not DRY and these classes may be unnecessary. If the core of the registration process doesn't change, we can create interface flexible enough to handle all cases by passing listeners that are being notified after registration process. Our service object could look like this:</p>


<p>``` ruby</p>

<p>class User::Registration</p>

<p>  attr_reader :logger, :listeners
  private :logger, :listeners</p>

<p>  def initialize(*listeners, **options)</p>

<pre><code>@listeners = listeners
@logger = options.fetch(:logger) { MyFancyCustomLogger }
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def register(aggregate)</p>

<pre><code># do some stuff common in all cases
notify_listeners(aggregate)
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  private</p>

<pre><code>def notify_listeners(aggregate)
  listeners.each { |listener| listener.notify(aggregate) }
end
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>We can pass any number of listeners to the constructor and inject dependencies if required. All listeners have to implement the same interface: <code>notify</code> method which takes one argument. The controller action for registering new user may look like this:</p>


<p>``` ruby
class UsersController &lt; ApplicationController</p>

<p>  def create</p>

<pre><code>user = User.new
form = User::RegistrationForm.new(user)
registration = User::Registration.new(
  AdminNewUserListener.new,
  SomeExternalServiceNewUserListener.new
  logger: MyFancyCustomLogger
)

if form.validate(params) &amp;&amp; registration.register(form)
  # success path
else
  # failure path
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>end
```</p>

<p>We've encapsulated additional logic in separate classes in form of listeners and created quite flexible interface - we need another action in registration process but only in one type of registration, not all of them? Just pass another listener into the constructor in controller.</p>




<h2>Extract context classes</h2>




<p>It often happens that you need an entity to play different roles, eg. the user can be a seller or a buyer, depending on the usecase. Instead of adding plenty of methods to the <code>User</code> class that are related only to the particular role, you can create context classes. Both sellers and buyers will probably share the same methods. One way to solve this problem could be inheritance but it would mean single table inheritance in this case (ActiveRecord model) and that's not what we need. However, we can use <code><a href="http://ruby-doc.org/stdlib-2.1.2/libdoc/delegate/rdoc/SimpleDelegator.html" target="_blank">SimpleDelegator</a></code> which would delegate all the method calls to the decorated object (user) if the decorator doesn't implement these methods:</p>


<p>``` ruby
class Seller &lt; SimpleDelegator</p>

<p>  def rating</p>

<pre><code># instead of rating_as_seller method in User class
positive_opinions_from_bought_items.to_f / opinions_from_bought_items.to_f
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>end</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>``` ruby
class Buyer &lt; SimpleDelegator</p>

<p>  def rating</p>

<pre><code># instead of rating_as_buyer method in User class
positive_opinions_from_seld_items.to_f / opinions_from_sold_items.to_f
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>end</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>We can also implement some convenience methods in <code>User</code> class to get user in approperiate context:</p>


<p>``` ruby
class User &lt; ActiveRecord::Base</p>

<p>  def to_buyer</p>

<pre><code>Buyer.new(self)
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def to_seller</p>

<pre><code>Seller.new(self)
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>end
```</p>

<h2>Trade long if/case statements for declarative dispatch</h2>




<p>Rather a structural implementation detail but still quite interesting. Imagine situation when you have to return proper status based on some conditions. You can of course use <code>case</code> statement but the problem with this approach is that the code is not really pretty, especially when you have multiple conditions for each status. For complex logic it might be better to handle such usecases with more declarative approach:</p>


<p>``` ruby
class User::SellerStatus</p>

<p>  attr_reader :user
  private :user</p>

<p>  def initialize(user)</p>

<pre><code>@user = user
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def call</p>

<pre><code>statuses_conditions.detect do |aggregate|
  conditions = aggregate.last
  conditions.all? { |condition| send(condition) }
end.first
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  private</p>

<pre><code>def statuses_conditions
  {
    super_seller: [
      :has_more_than_1000_opinions?,
      :has_more_than_95_percent_positive_opinions_as_seller?
    ],
    blacklisted_seller: [ 
      :has_at_least_10_opinion_as_seller?,
      :has_more_than_50_precent_or_equal_negative_opinions_as_seller?
    ],
    new: [
      :has_less_than_10_opinion_as_seller?,
    ],
    no_status: []
  }
end

def has_more_than_1000_opinions?
  # some code
end

def has_more_than_95_percent_positive_opinions_as_seller?
  # some code
end

def has_at_least_10_opinion_as_seller?
  # some code
end

def has_more_than_50_precent_or_equal_negative_opinions_as_seller?
  # some code
end

def has_less_than_10_opinion_as_seller?
  # some code
end
</code></pre>

<p>end</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>The <code>detect</code> enumerator (aliased also as <code>find</code>) will return the first element for which the block returns true. In this case all the conditions must be satisfied to return true.</p>




<p>Instead of using bunch of private methods, you can move these methods to policy objects and change the receiver of the message to be the policy, not <code>self</code>:</p>


<p>``` ruby</p>

<p>def call
  policy = User::SellerPolicy.new(user)
  statuses_conditions.detect do |aggregate|</p>

<pre><code>conditions = aggregate.last
conditions.all? { |condition| policy.public_send(condition) }
</code></pre>

<p>  end.first
end</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>I like the clarity of this approach - you can immediately say what are the necessary conditions for each status without multiple <code>&&</code> operators in case statement which would make it harder to read.</p>




<h2>Wrapping up</h2>




<p>I've shown some simple and common techniques I use in almost everyday coding. I hope that you will find them useful and will keep the code clean.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Structuring Rails applications]]></title>
    <link href="https://karolgalanciak.com/blog/2013/10/06/structuring-rails-applications/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-06T15:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://karolgalanciak.com/blog/2013/10/06/structuring-rails-applications</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There've been a lot of discussions recently about applying Object Oriented Programming in Rails applications, how ActiveRecord callbacks make testing painful and how Rails makes it hard to do OOP the right way. Is it really true? Rails makes everything easy - you can easily write terrible code, which will be a maintenance nightmare, but is also easy to apply good practices, especially with available gems. What is the good way then to extract logic in Rails applications and the best place to put it?</p>




<!--more-->


<p></p>

<h2>Standard structure</h2>




<p>By default we have four directories where we can put our code: models, views, controllers and helpers. The basic explanation of them is following:</p>




<ul>  
  <li>Models - dealing with database, validations, repository, persistence.</li>
  <li>Controllers - parsing requests, sessions, rendering views etc.</li> 
  <li>Views - user interface, data presenting.</li>
  <li>Helpers - place to put reusable methods for views.</li>
</ul>




<p>Does it mean these are the only places where you can put your code? No! It's just a default structure with basic parts of your application. You can easily extend it by creating new directories and then adding them to autoload paths, e.g.: </p>


<p><code>ruby
  config.autoload_paths += Dir["#{AppName::Application.config.root}/app/usecases"]
</code></p>

<h2>How about lib directory?</h2>




<p>Unless you are extracting something to a gem, I would discourage you from putting anything there. Some developers put in the lib all the code that doesn't belong to models/controllers/helpers, but if something is part of your application why not add it to the app directory?</p>




<h2>Skinny controllers, fat models</h2>




<p>The design mantra for the last few years in Rails was to move logic from controllers to models. Well, it's partially a good thing - skinny controllers are clear, easy to test and maintain, but why should models be like 1000 lines of code with tens of responsibilities (and no, everything concerning User is not a single responsibility)? It makes models in most cases the most problematic layer in Rails applications. They often include a lot of unrelated methods, conditional validations, cross-models operations, callbacks etc. - all the things that ActiveRecord makes really easy to add. So, the important question is:</p>




<h2>Is ActiveRecord evil?</h2>




<p><p>ActiveRecord is a wonderful ORM, which indeed makes everythings easy. But with great power comes great responsibility. Think about callbacks: you can add new logic in a blink of an eye and it does the job. So you keep adding other callbacks until you discover that there are some cases where you don&rsquo;t want them to be executed. So you add conditionals or bypass-like methods. After some time, the logic in callbacks is so complexed that you waste few hours with other developers to understand why something was executed at all. If other developers join the project, it is even harder for them to understand what model class really does. But it isn&rsquo;t the worst part. Think about some gems and their integration with Rails. Often it means extending models with another callbacks. Here are some real world problems:</p>

<p><p>Imagine the situation where you need to implement the ability for admin to register other users and the application uses Devise gem for authentication. Furthermore, the <code> Confirmable</code> module is included in the <code>User</code>  class. Accidentally, you forgot to pass a date to <code>:confirmed_at</code> field or use <code>confirm!</code>  method. What happens then? The confirmation email is sent to all registered users. Oops, welcome to the wonderful world of callbacks. I don&rsquo;t want to criticize Devise, because it is a great gem, which I use in almost every project, but I am not sure if sending emails being directly coupled to the model layer was a good design decision. In docs you can read about the <code>skip_confirmation!</code> method and if you use external gem for such a critical part of your application, you should read the entire docs, but it can be really suprising, that the confirmation email is sent in all cases, even if you create user from Rails Console. Oh, and guess what happens if you want to change one&rsquo;s email from the console and <code> reconfirmable</code> option is enabled? The confirmation email is sent&hellip; Well, remember about reading docs, especially when the gem may include callbacks.</p></p>

<p><p>Any other examples? Of course. So, you want to implement a generic forum. There is a gem called Forem, which provides you with basic forum functionality. And one day you want to change state of some posts to be approved. So you enter Rails Console and using <code> update</code>  or <code>update_attributes</code> you perform the update. What happens then? There is a callback in <code>Forem::Post</code>  model:</p></p>

<p><code>ruby
  after_save :email_topic_subscribers, :if =&gt; Proc.new { |p| p.approved? &amp;&amp; !p.notified? }
</code></p>

<p><p>A lot of emails have been just sent! That was really unexpected. If you are used to  skipping callbacks in such situatons by using <code>update_columns</code> method or any other way, you are safe, but callbacks are so tighly coupled to models, that you cannot be sure if you are safe, even in console. What is the conslusion? Beware of callbacks. And read docs and code of the gems you use :).</p></p>

<p><p>So, how to avoid unexpected situations and have clean and understandable code?</p></p>

<p><h2>Structuring Rails applications &ndash; my way</h2></p>

<p><p>I&rsquo;ve been working on several projects and the best solution in terms of maintenance, understandability and ease of testing is the following:</p></p>

<p><h3>Models</h3></p>

<p><p>I use models for: factory methods, queries, scopes, general validations, which are always applicable e.g. presence and uniqueness validations for fields with <code>null: false</code>  and / or <code>unique: true</code> constraints, also &ldquo;domain constraints&rdquo;, especially with many-to-many associations. The example of domain constraint is assigning users, who belong to the same organization, to some subgroups &ndash; assigning users from other organizations is prohibited. Putting this kind of logic in controllers' before_filters or permission classes is not enough for me, I want to ensure the integrity of the data and make it impossible to bypass this restriction. Here is an example: we have <code>User</code>  model and <code>Group</code> model and the many-to-many relationship between them, which is established by <code>has_many , through: </code> macro with <code>GroupsUsers</code>  join model. Also, users and groups belong to <code>Organization</code>. Here is a validation for creating relation in join model:</p></p>

<p>``` ruby
class GroupsUsers &lt; ActiveRecord::Base</p>

<p>  belongs_to :group
  belongs_to :user</p>

<p>  validates :group, presence: true
  validates :user,  presence: true
  validate :ensure_valid_organization</p>

<p>  private</p>

<pre><code>def ensure_valid_organization
  if user.organization != group.organization
    raise InvalidOrganizationError, "User's organization does not match Group's organization."
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>end
```
<p>Other example of domain constraint is validation of inclusion.</p></p>

<p><p>Sometimes I do use callbacks. The basic rule when applying callbacks for me is to use them for processing some data, which should always take place. In most cases, it is limited to three callbacks:</p></p>

<p><code>ruby
before_save   :create_parameterized_name
after_save    :calculate_statistics
after_destroy :calculate_statistics
</code></p>

<p><p>Pretty easy to understand: everytime the record is saved, I want to have parameterized form of name, e.g. for a slug. Also, after the record is saved or destroyed, I want the statistics to be updated. For instance, in real estate search engine application, investment has many apartments and I want to keep track of total count of apartments, average price, minimum and maximum price etc. without performing calculations each time. And one more callback concerning associations: <code>dependent: :destroy</code>  option. It is pretty useful and keeps the integrity of data, but you have to be sure when using it. If you think for a moment, these are &ldquo;low-level&rdquo; callbacks &ndash; they don&rsquo;t concern business logic and are something that you would like to have on a database level. It can be also achieved by using trigger functions in the database, but Rails callbacks are much easier to handle.</p></p>

<p><p>This is not the only right way for using callbacks, if you are absolutely sure that something should really be executed as callback, feel free to use them, but please, don&rsquo;t send notifications, don&rsquo;t connect with Facebook API or download files from Dropbox in callbacks. You will be safe, the logic will be easy to understand and testing will be much easier.</p></p>

<p><p>Sometimes I use model as an interface for some service objects / usecases / whatever you call it. Here is an example: </p></p>

<p>``` ruby
class Article &lt; ActiveRecord::Base</p>

<p>  def publish(publisher = DefaultPublisher)</p>

<pre><code>publisher.new(self).publish
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>end
```</p>

<p><p>It is a great way to have a flexibility in publishing articles &ndash; by dependency injection we can control, how it is being published &ndash; just pass publisher class as a strategy. Having default publisher makes it easy to use: just call <code>article.publish</code> . Also, calling <code>article.publish</code> in e.g. controller feels much better than calling <code>DefaultPublisher(article).publish</code>. If you have very simple logic, like this one:</p></p>

<p><code>ruby
def publish
  self.published_at = DateTime.now if self.published_at.blank?
  self.save
end
</code></p>

<p><p>don&rsquo;t bother with extracting it to external class, it would be pointless.</p></p>

<p><h3>Controllers</h3></p>

<p><p>Everything related to parsing requests, sessions, rendering templates, redirecting and flash messages should be put in controllers. What about application logic? In most cases it should be limited to a control-flow, for example:</p></p>

<p>``` ruby
class ArticlesController &lt; ApplicationController</p>

<p>  def create</p>

<pre><code>@article = Article.find(params[:id])

if @article.save
  flash[:notice] = "You have successfully created an article."
  redirect_to articles_path
else
  render :new
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>end
```</p>

<p><p>Depending on the action, it could be much more complex. Consider the following:</p></p>

<p>``` ruby</p>

<p>class OrdersController &lt; ApplicationController</p>

<p>  def buy</p>

<pre><code>order = Order.new(order_params)
order_proccesor = BooksOrderProcessor.new(order, current_user)

begin
  order_processor.pay
rescue BooksOrderProcessor::InsufficientAmount
  flash.now[:error] = "Not enough books are available."
  render :new
rescue BooksOrderProcessor::InsufficientFounds
  flash[:error] = "You have run out of funds."
  redirect_to profile_path(current_user)
else
  flash[:notice] = "You have bought a book."
  redirect_to books_path
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  private</p>

<pre><code>def order_params
  params.require(:order).permit!
end
</code></pre>

<p>end</p>

<p>```</p>

<p><p>It is still good, such control-flow can take place in a controller, but order processing logic cannot. But what should be done with creating articles and sending notification or logging action? If it is only one additional line of code with method call like <code>Tracker.register(&ldquo;create&rdquo;, @article)</code> or <code>NewArticleNotfier.delay.notify</code>, for example:</p></p>

<p>``` ruby</p>

<p>class ArticlesController &lt; ApplicationController</p>

<p>  def create</p>

<pre><code>@article = Article.find(params[:id])

if @article.save
  NewArticleNotfier.delay.notify
  flash[:notice] = "You have successfully created an article."
  redirect_to articles_path
else
  render :new
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>end</p>

<p>```
<p>don&rsquo;t extract it to usecase or service object, it is ok to keep it in a controller.</p></p>

<p><h3>Cells</h3></p>

<p><p>You have probably had many situations with setting up the same instance variables in several controller actions for some widgets like: tags cloud, recent articles, recent comments, top visited articles etc. and it can be really inconvenient. Fortunately, there&rsquo;s a great gem: Cells, which are like mini controllers. Consider the following:</p></p>

<p>``` ruby
class ArticlesCell &lt; Cell::Rails</p>

<p>  def top_visited</p>

<pre><code>@articles = Article.top_visited
render
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>end</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>In cells/articles/top_visited.html.haml/erb you put the related markup and invoke cells from views by:</p>

<p>``` ruby</p>

<p>= render_cell :articles, :top_five</p>

<p>```</p>

<p><p>Another great thing about cells is that you can inject a dependency: </p></p>

<p><code>ruby
= render_cell :widgets, :newsletter, newsletter_form: @newsletter_form
</code></p>

<p><p>You can easily create a widget with newsletter submission form with enabled remote: true option and then render error messages or notice message that the email has been submitted.</p></p>

<p><h3>Helpers</h3></p>

<p><p>In most cases I use helpers to extract some things that aren&rsquo;t related to any particular model &ndash; rendering flash messages, titles, html templates etc., so nothing really fancy. Everything else should be extracted to the presenters/decorators. The good example of helper is the following:</p></p>

<p>``` ruby
def section_marker(text)
  content_tag(:h2, class: &ldquo;section-marker&rdquo;) do</p>

<pre><code>"&lt;i class='icon-align-left'&gt;&lt;/i&gt; #{text}".html_safe
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p><p>Before each section I had to insert header with nested icon and some text, so instead of writing the same thing several times, I extracted it to a helper, which is much cleaner. It doesn&rsquo;t belong to any model, so helper is a good place to put this kind of code. If you use Boostrap a lot, you may consider writing <code>modal_activator</code> method:</p></p>

<p><code>ruby
def modal_activator(text, path, options)
  link_to(text, path, options.merge(role: "button", "data-toggle" =&gt; "modal"))
end
</code></p>

<p><h3>Presenters/Decorators</h3></p>

<p><p>Helpers aren&rsquo;t the best place to extract logic related to models &ndash; the code in helpers tends to be messy and difficult to maintain and test. The good solution would be to use Presenters &ndash; objects that encapsulate presentation logic in a neat way. There&rsquo;s a gem that is perfect for this kind of problems: Draper. Just create a decorator class, like <code>UserDecorator</code>: </p></p>

<p>``` ruby
class UserDecorator &lt; Draper::Base</p>

<p>  delegate_all
  decorates :user</p>

<p>  def link_to_edit</p>

<pre><code>h.link_to("Edit", user_path(model))
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def full_name</p>

<pre><code>if model.name.present? and model.surname.present?
  "#{model.name} #{model.surname}"
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def display</p>

<pre><code>full_name || model.email
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>end</p>

<p>```</p>

<p><p>Looks great! You don&rsquo;t have to keep presentation logic in helpers or even worse in models.
You have an access to Rails helpers via h, also all method calls are delegated to model if it isn&rsquo;t implemented in a decorator. To decorate model just use <code>decorate</code> method:</p></p>

<p><code>ruby
@user = User.find(params[:id]).decorate
</code></p>

<p><p>You can also decorate collection by using <code>decorate</code> method.</p></p>

<p><h3>Forms</h3></p>

<p><p>Imagine a situation where you need a form concerning more than one model. Also, some conditional validation is required. What would you do? Probably use nested attributes and add some complex validations, which would make model messy and maybe cause some bugs. There&rsquo;s much better way to do it: use form object and Reform gem. Then you can create following objects:</p></p>

<p>``` ruby
require &lsquo;reform/form/coercion&rsquo;
require &lsquo;reform/rails&rsquo;</p>

<p>class UserRegistrationForm &lt; Reform::Form</p>

<p>  include DSL
  include Reform::Form::ActiveRecord
  include Reform::Form::Coercion</p>

<p>  properties [:email, :name, :country_id],  on: :user
  property :birth_date,        on: :user_profile, type: Date
  properties [:age, :photo],   on: :user_profile</p>

<p>  validates :email, :photo, :birth_date, :name, :age, presence: true
  validates :age, numericality: true
  validates :email, uniqueness: { case_sensitive: false }</p>

<p>  model :user</p>

<p>  def countries_collection</p>

<pre><code>Country.all.pluck(:id, :name)
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def persist!(params)</p>

<pre><code>if validate(params)
  begin
    save do |data, map|
      UserRegistration.new.register!(
        User.new(map[:user]),
        UserProfile.new(map[:user_profile])
      )
    end
  rescue UserRegistration::RegistrationFailed
    false
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>end</p>

<p>```</p>

<p><p>By using Reform gem, you can easily create clean form objects, which would deal with validations, coercions (thanks to Virtus) and persisting data concerning multiple models. Also, you can put some form interface logic here &ndash; consider <code>countries_collection</code> method: instead of passing: <code>collection: Country.all.pluck(:id, :name)</code> to the select field, you can just pass <code>form_object.countries_collection</code>. This example is trivial, but if you had some filtering and ordering logic needed to display collection, then it would be great way to keep everything clean. Using form objects doesn&rsquo;t change control-flow in controllers:</p></p>

<p>``` ruby
class UsersController &lt; ApplicationController</p>

<p>  def new</p>

<pre><code>@registration = registration_form
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def create</p>

<pre><code>@registration = registration_form

if @registration.persist!(user_params)
  redirect_to root_path
else
  render :new
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  private</p>

<pre><code>def registration_form
  UserRegistrationForm.new(user: User.new, user_profile: UserProfile.new)
end

def user_params
  params.require(:user).permit!
end
</code></pre>

<p>end
```</p>

<p><p>Form objects are also great way to extract search forms and logic related to filtering. Reform can deal with <code>has_many</code> associations and nested collections, so it is pretty powerful. However, there are some cases where you would still want to use <code>accepts_nested_attributes_for</code> &ndash; when you need funcionality provided by nested_form gem. It is not really clean to use <code>accepts_nested_attributes_for</code> macro, but the benefits are great. In other cases, form object is a way to go.</p></p>

<p><h3>Uploaders</h3></p>

<p><p>For file uploading I use Carrierwave where the uploaders' configuration is kept in the /uploaders directory. That&rsquo;s a really good approach, because thumb-processing strategy etc. has nothing to do with ActiveRecord model, so there&rsquo;s no reason to keep this kind of information there. Here is an example of general uploader:</p></p>

<p>``` ruby
class ApplicationUploader &lt; CarrierWave::Uploader::Base</p>

<p>  include CarrierWave::MiniMagick</p>

<p>  storage :file</p>

<p>  CarrierWave::SanitizedFile.sanitize_regexp = /[^[:word:].-+]/</p>

<p>  def store_dir</p>

<pre><code>"system/#{Rails.env}/#{model.class.to_s.underscore}/#{mounted_as}/#{model.id}"
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def extension_white_list</p>

<pre><code>%w(jpg jpeg gif png pdf tiff tif eps bmp ps)
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  private</p>

<pre><code>def rgbify
  begin
    manipulate! do |img|  
      img.colorspace "sRGB"
      img
    end
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>end</p>

<p>```</p>

<p><p>And example of some images uploader:</p></p>

<p>``` ruby</p>

<p>class LogoUploader &lt; ApplicationUploader</p>

<p>  def filename</p>

<pre><code>"original.#{model.logo.file.extension}" if original_filename
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  version :thumb do</p>

<pre><code>process :rgbify
process :resize_to_fill =&gt; [100, 100]
process :convert =&gt; 'jpg'
def full_filename(for_file)
  "thumb.jpg"
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>end</p>

<p>```</p>

<p><p>Looks great and doesn&rsquo;t clutter models with unrelated image-processing configuration options.</p></p>

<p><h3>Services</h3></p>

<p><p>You may expect that in /services directory so called service-objects would be placed. Well, not really. I prefer to call them (service objects) usecases and in /services I put some wrappers concerning third party APIs. In one application I&rsquo;ve been working on, I had to deal with Google Calendar integration and the adapter layer for performing requests to GC was a service, for instance:</p></p>

<p>``` ruby</p>

<p>module GoogleCalendar
  class Calendars</p>

<pre><code>attr_reader :client
def initialize(client)
  @client = client
end

#some other methods

def patch(calendar_id, calendar_data)
  client.execute(api_method: client.service.calendars.patch), body: calendar_data,
    parameters: { "calendarId" =&gt; calendar_id }, headers: {'Content-Type' =&gt; 'application/json'})      
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end<br/>
end</p>

<p>```</p>

<p><p>In smaller applications you won&rsquo;t probably need this layer, otherwise it is a neat way to separate services from the rest of the application.</p></p>

<p><h3>Usecases</h3></p>

<p><p>This is a place where most of the business logic should be extracted &ndash; almost everything that would be in models, according to &ldquo;skinny controllers, far models&rdquo;. The benefits of using usecase objects / service objects are great &ndash; they area easy to undestand and maintain, testing is simple and don&rsquo;t lead to unexpected actions (like the ones I pointed out in callbacks). Let&rsquo;s take a look again at the user registration process from form object, the implementation of <code>UserRegistration</code> could be following:</p></p>

<p>``` ruby</p>

<p>class UserRegistration</p>

<p>  attr_reader :admin_notifier, :external_service_notifier
  def initialize(notifiers = {})</p>

<pre><code>@admin_notifier = notifiers.fetch(:admin_notifier) { AdminNotifier.new }
@external_service_notifier = notifiers.fetch(:external_service_notifier) { ExternalServiceNotifier.new }
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def register!(user, profile)</p>

<pre><code>profile.user = user
ActiveRecord::Base.transaction do
  begin
    user.save!
    profile.save!
  rescue
    raise UserRegistration::RegistrationFailed
  end
end
notify_admin
notify_external_service
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def notify_admin</p>

<pre><code>admin_notifier.notify(user)
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def notify_external_service</p>

<pre><code>external_service_notifier.new_user(user, profile)
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  class RegistrationFailed &lt; Exception
  end</p>

<p>end</p>

<p>```</p>

<p><p>Let&rsquo;s discuss some design choices here: in the constructor I added a possibility to inject some notifiers and provide reasonable defaults using <code>Hash#fetch</code> method to avoid nils. In <code>register</code> method I wrap the persistence process in <code>ActiveRecord::Base.transaction</code>, to ensure that user is not created without the profile if any error occurs (notice the bang methods), if it fails, the exception is raised. Then, some notifiers are called, one is a mailer, the other one connects with an external service and does some stuff. They should be executed asynchronously, in Delayed Job, Resque or Sidekiq to make sure they are completed if failure occurs &ndash; there might be a temporary problem with connecting to Gmail, Facebook, Twitter etc. but it&rsquo;s not a reason for an entire registration process to fail.</p></p>

<p><h3>Policies</h3></p>

<p><p>Policy objects are a bit special &ndash; it&rsquo;s a decorator, but Draper decorators are not the best place to put them, because they concern presentation logic. Models, except small applications, are also wrong place to write policy logic as they encapsulate important domain logic which can be quite complex. So it is a good idea to create separate objects &ndash; policy objects. Depending on the size of your application, you may have several policy objects or just one for a model, here is an example:</p></p>

<p>``` ruby</p>

<p>class InvestmentPromotionPolicy</p>

<p>  attr_reader :investment, :clock
  def initialize(investment, clock = DateTime)</p>

<pre><code>@investment = investment
@clock = clock
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def promoted?</p>

<pre><code>valid_promotion_date? and owner_promotable?
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def owner_promotable?</p>

<pre><code>investment.owner.active_for_promotion?
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def promotion_status</p>

<pre><code>case
when promoted?
  :promoted
when valid_promotion_date? and !owner_promotable?
  :pending_for_promotion
else
  :not_promoted
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  private</p>

<pre><code>def valid_promotion_date?
  (investment.promotion_starts_at..investment.promotion_ends_at).cover? clock.now
end
</code></pre>

<p>end</p>

<p>```</p>

<p><p>In the constructor I pass an investment and the clock, which by default is <code>DateTime</code>. I had some issues with concept of time, especially in policy objects where I had to implement own <code>Clock</code>, because <code>DateTime</code> was not sufficient, so just to be on a safe side, I add a possibility for a dependency injection. It doesn&rsquo;t increase a complexity of the class and I wouldn&rsquo;t consider it as a premature optimization. Then we have some methods that encapsulate promotion logic and one that returns proper status. You will probably use policy objects in many cases &ndash; e.g. <code>promotion_status</code> method looks like it could be used in a presenter, which would display proper content, depending on the returned status and the <code>promoted?</code> method could be used in the usecases or in a model class method that would return promoted investments. You can use policy objects in many ways: inject into a model and delegate method calls:</p></p>

<p>``` ruby</p>

<p>class Investment &lt; ActiveRecord::Base</p>

<p>  delegate :promoted?, :owner_promotable?, :promotion_status to: :promotion_policy</p>

<p>  # some methods</p>

<p>  private</p>

<pre><code>def promotion_policy
  @promotion_policy ||= InvestmentPromotionPolicy.new(self)
end
</code></pre>

<p>end</p>

<p>```</p>

<p><p>In the same way you can use them in presenters if you don&rsquo;t want to keep it in the model layer. They can also be injected as a dependency into a usecase. Choose whatever suits you better and the complexity of the application.</p></p>

<p><h3>Value objects</h3></p>

<p><p>In many applications you may encounter a situation where a concept deserves own abstraction and whose equality isn&rsquo;t based on identity but on the value, some examples would be Ruby&rsquo;s <code>Date</code> or <code>Money</code> concept, typical for e-commerce applications. Extraction to a value object (or domain model) is a great convenience. Imagine a situation where you have a hierarchy of roles of users &ndash; you will probably want to compare the roles if one is &ldquo;greater&rdquo; than another to decide, if some action can be performed &ndash; the <code>RoleRank</code> would solve this problem:</p></p>

<p>``` ruby</p>

<p>class RoleRank</p>

<p>  include Comparable</p>

<p>  ROLES = %w(superadmin admin junior_admin user guest)</p>

<p>  attr_reader :value
  def initialize(role)</p>

<pre><code>check_role_existence(role)
@value = value
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def &lt;=>(other_role)</p>

<pre><code>ROLES.index(other_role.value) &lt;=&gt; ROLES.index(value)
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def to_s</p>

<pre><code>value
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  class InvalidRole &lt; Exception
  end</p>

<p>  private</p>

<pre><code>def check_role_existence(specified_role)
  unless ROLES.include? specified_role
    raise RoleRank::InvalidRole, "Specified Role Doesn't Exist"
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>end</p>

<p>```</p>

<p><p>Looks great. The <code>Comparable</code> module and <code>&lt;=></code> takes care of implementing comparison operators. You can add a method with ranked role to the user model: </p></p>

<p>``` ruby
class User &lt; ActiveRecord::Base</p>

<p>  def role</p>

<pre><code>@role ||= RoleRank.new(permission_level)
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>end
```</p>

<p><p>and then compare users' roles:</p></p>

<p><code>ruby
user = User.new(permission_level: "superadmin")
other_user = User.new(permission_level: "admin")
user.role &gt; other_user.role =&gt; true
</code>
<h3>What about Observers and Concerns?</h3></p>

<p><p>There are two more ways to extract logic &ldquo;the standard way&rdquo;: observers (removed from Rails 4) and concerns. Observers aren&rsquo;t really different from callbacks, except they are more difficult to deal with &ndash; you will probably forget that you&rsquo;ve used them and debugging or following the application logic would be even harder than in callbacks and I&rsquo;m glad they were removed. And the new thing in Rails 4: concerns. They are great, expecially for shared behaviour. When you need to parameterize field name in several models, you can extract it to a module in concerns, and then include Parameterizable concern, some custom finders and factory methods also can be extracted into concerns. If you use the same before_filters in more than controller, extracting them to the concerns would be a good idea. In Presenters, such concern as <code>Presenters::Publishable</code> would be beneficial when you have articles, posts and some other models that act in a similar way, so introducing concerns and encouragement to extract similar behaviour was definitely a good idea.</p></p>

<p><h3>Any other application layers?</h3></p>

<p><p>Depending on your application, you may introduce additional layers like JSON representations of models, jobs that should be done in a background or XML importers, but they can be considered as presentation logic (jsons) or usecases / services (importers, background jobs). If XML importers are important part of your business logic, then maybe extracting them from usecases and treating in a special way would be beneficial.</p></p>

<p><h2>Wrapping up</h3></p>

<p><p>The concepts mentioned here might not be popular among some developers and be considered as over-engineering. When writing simple CMS, introducing services, form objects etc. probably is a premature optimization and models / contollers / helpers and maybe presenters would be sufficient, including writing business logic in ActiveRecord callbacks. But in more complex application applying some OOP techniques can save you (and other developers you work with) from a lot of problems.</p></p>

<p><h2>Further reading</h2></p>

<p><ul>
  <li><a href="http://blog.codeclimate.com/blog/2012/10/17/7-ways-to-decompose-fat-activerecord-models" target="_blank">7 Patterns to Refactor Fat ActiveRecord Models</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://samuelmullen.com/2013/05/the-problem-with-rails-callbacks/" target="_blank">The Problem With Rails Callbacks</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://blog.steveklabnik.com/posts/2011-09-06-the-secret-to-rails-oo-design" target="_blank">The Secret to Rails OO Design</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://objectsonrails.com" target="_blank">Objects On Rails</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://solnic.eu/2011/08/01/making-activerecord-models-thin.html" target="_blank">Making ActiveRecord Models Thin</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://blog.arkency.com/2013/09/services-what-they-are-and-why-we-need-them/" target="_blank">Services &ndash; what are they and why we need them?</a></li>
</ul></p>

<p><p class="meta small-p">Changelog: 09-10-2013 &ndash; Use <code>Comparable</code> module and <code>&lt;=></code> method for implementing comparison operators in RankedRole. Provide better example in <code>OrdersController</code>. Thanks <a href="http://www.reddit.com/user/yxhuvud" rel="nofollow" target="_blank">yxhuvud</a> for suggestions.</p></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
