<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Rails | Karol Galanciak - Ruby on Rails and Ember.js consultant]]></title>
  <link href="https://karolgalanciak.com/blog/categories/rails/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://karolgalanciak.com/"/>
  <updated>2019-08-18T11:17:07+02:00</updated>
  <id>https://karolgalanciak.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Karol Galanciak]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Messages on Rails Part 3: RabbitMQ]]></title>
    <link href="https://karolgalanciak.com/blog/2019/06/23/messages-on-rails-part-3-rabbitmq/"/>
    <updated>2019-06-23T18:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://karolgalanciak.com/blog/2019/06/23/messages-on-rails-part-3-rabbitmq</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the <a href="https://karolgalanciak.com/blog/2019/02/24/messages-on-rails-part-1-introduction-to-kafka-and-rabbitmq/">first part</a> of this series, we were exploring some potential options for <strong>communication between services</strong> &ndash; what their advantages and disadvantages are, why <strong>HTTP API</strong> is not necessarily the best possible choice and suggesting that <strong>asynchronous messaging</strong> might be a better solution, using, e.g. <strong>RabbitMQ</strong> and <strong>Kafka</strong>. We&rsquo;ve already covered <strong>Kafka</strong> in the <a href="https://karolgalanciak.com/blog/2019/04/07/messages-on-rails-part-2-kafka/">part 2</a>, now it&rsquo;s the time for <strong>RabbitMQ</strong>.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>What is RabbitMQ, and how does it work?</h2>

<p>RabbitMQ is a general purpose message broker supporting multiple protocols, yet, we are going to focus mostly on AMQP, which is the one that is the most typically used. It implements a smart broker/dumb consumer model. Unlike Kafka, it means that the broker is responsible for delivering messages to the right place. Also, the <code>queue</code> in Rabbit is what you would naturally consider being a queue &ndash; it&rsquo;s not database-like storage as Kafka topics are.</p>

<p>So what does publishing and consuming a message actually mean?</p>

<p>In the first step, a <code>producer</code> publishes a <code>message</code> &ndash; this can be a JSON message or whatever else that could be sent. This message is delivered to a <code>queue</code>, from which <code>consumers</code> can read it and process it. After the message is consumed, it&rsquo;s gone from the queue.</p>

<p>If this sounds to you like Redis and Sidekiq, you would be quite right. Actually, Redis could also be used as a message queue for communication between apps, although that might not be necessarily the best idea as being a message queue is not its primary purpose.</p>

<p>Why is RabbitMQ is so unique though, and what can it do that Redis or even Kafka can&rsquo;t do?</p>

<p>One of the key characteristics of RabbitMQ is that producers don&rsquo;t push messages directly to the queues. Instead, producers send messages to another layer called <code>exchanges</code>. This has quite profound consequences on the way RabbitMQ can be used and the features it offers:</p>

<ul>
<li>Producers don&rsquo;t need to be aware of all the queues where the message should be delivered, which means excellent decoupling between producers and consumers and ease of use</li>
<li>Without exchanges, it would not be possible to easily implement a publish-subscribe pattern where multiple consumers need to process a given message. Instead, you would have pretty much something like in Sidekiq &ndash; when the message is pushed to the queue, the workers compete for it, and it gets processed only once, there is no case of multiple workers handling the same message. However, competing consumers pattern is still possible in RabbitMQ (we will see it later but rather as something to avoid in that particular case).</li>
<li>Having extra layer in-between allows flexible routing and the implementation of some rules telling how and under what conditions consumers want to have messages delivered.</li>
</ul>


<p>In general, we could visualize the flow in RabbitMQ in the following way:</p>

<p class="img-center-wrapper">
  <img class="img-center" src="/images/messages_on_rails_part_3/rabbitmq_generalization.png" title="RabbitMQ" alt="RabbitMQ">
</p>




<p class="center">
  <a href="https://karolgalanciak.com/images/messages_on_rails_part_3/rabbitmq_generalization.png" target="_blank">See in better quality</a>
</p>


<h2>Publishing/Receiving messages and exchanges</h2>

<p>Ability to implement a publish-subscribe pattern is a natural consequence of having exchanges. As we could see on the graph above, the producer is not aware of all of the queues to which the messages will be delivered. It might be even the case that there are no queues at all that would be interested in any message!</p>

<p>For the queues to receive messages, we need to create a relationship between that queue and the exchange. In RabbitMQ it&rsquo;s called a <code>binding</code>.</p>

<p>So far, we know that the publisher sends a message to the exchange and exchange delivers the messages to queues that are bound to it. But what are the rules here that would determine to which queues exactly the message should be delivered to (besides the fact that the queues must have established a binding with the exchange)?</p>

<p>To achieve that, we have four types of exchange types that have a bit different behavior:</p>

<ol>
<li><code>fanout</code> exchange &ndash; it just delivers a message to all the queues that are bound to it.</li>
<li><code>direct</code> &ndash; a given queue might be only interested in some particular type of messages that could be filtered out by some criteria. E.g., you might be publishing logs with different levels, just like in <code>Rails.logger</code> where you have <code>debug</code>, <code>info</code>, <code>fatal</code> etc. severity levels. In that case, there might be a queue that wants to receive only <code>fatal</code> logs, and another one might want to receive just <code>debug</code> logs. Instead of letting the consumer do the filtering itself, we can let RabbitMQ do it by specifying a <code>routing key</code> in the message. We could publish logs with routing keys such as <code>log.debug</code> and <code>log.fatal</code> and let the queues bind accordingly using that routing key as a <code>binding key</code>. That&rsquo;s exactly what a <code>direct</code> exchange is about. However, what if we want to have a third queue that would be interested in all types of logs? In that case, we would need to use another kind of exchange:</li>
<li><code>topic</code> &ndash; it&rsquo;s the exchange that allows receiving messages based on the patterns. In case of the example of logs, the queue that would be interested in all kinds of logs could create a binding with <code>log.*</code> routing key. And what if it were interested in receiving all messages (i.e., work as a <code>fanout</code> exchange, even though we are using <code>topic</code> exchange here)? RabbitMQ has us covered, we could use a special routing key: <code>#</code> and that would be enough. Also, the <code>topic</code> exchange can also act as a <code>direct</code> one &ndash; there is nothing preventing a queue from binding with a full routing key name, so using more &ldquo;advanced&rdquo; exchange type is only adding more options and flexibility, it doesn&rsquo;t take away the features of &ldquo;simpler&rdquo; ones.</li>
<li><code>headers</code> exchange type &ndash; arguably a less common one, it&rsquo;s quite similar to <code>topic</code> exchange, although the filtering is performed based on the values of the headers instead of routing keys.</li>
</ol>


<h2>Using RabbitMQ in Ruby/Rails apps</h2>

<h3>RPC with RabbitMQ</h3>

<p>There is one somewhat unexpected feature of RabbitMQ (at least if you focus on async messaging) &ndash; Remote Procedure Call (RPC). That way you can implement synchronous request-reply flow, just like with HTTP APIs. So if it&rsquo;s just like good ol' HTTP API, why would you even consider RPCs via RabbitMQ?</p>

<p>Sometimes you might not need REST API as you might be interested only in executing a specific set of commands/procedures in another service that don&rsquo;t easily map to resources that you would expose in REST API. It is especially true if you develop a private API which is not going to be exposed to Third Party Users, so there is little concern for &ldquo;externalization&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s check a quick example to see it in action. To make RPC with RabbitMQ what we need to do is to publish a message and specify a reply-to (callback) queue to which the server will reply.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s implement a classic: a Fibonacci sequence server to which the clients will be sending the numbers and expecting the result in the response. One of the super simple ways to implement RPCs in Ruby is to do it via <a href="https://github.com/peejaybee/bunny_burrow">bunny_borrow gem</a>. To see it almost right away in action, you could add it to a Gemfile of any Rails application, open two Rails console processes, execute this code in the first one:</p>

<p>``` rb
class Fibonacci
  def self.calculate(number, accum = {})</p>

<pre><code>return number if number == 0 || number == 1
accum[number] ||= calculate(number - 1, accum) + calculate(number-2, accum)
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end</p>

<p>rpc_server = BunnyBurrow::Server.new do |server|
  server.rabbitmq_url = &ldquo;amqp://guest:guest@localhost:5672&rdquo;
  server.rabbitmq_exchange = &ldquo;fibonacci_sequence&rdquo;
  server.logger = Logger.new(STDOUT)
end</p>

<p>rpc_server.subscribe(&ldquo;fibonacci.route&rdquo;) do |payload|
  BunnyBurrow::Server.create_response.tap do |response|</p>

<pre><code>response[:result] = Fibonacci.calculate(JSON.parse(payload).fetch("number"))
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end</p>

<p>rpc_server.wait
```</p>

<p>and this in the second one:</p>

<p>``` rb
rpc_client = BunnyBurrow::Client.new do |client|
  client.rabbitmq_url =  &ldquo;amqp://guest:guest@localhost:5672&rdquo;
  client.rabbitmq_exchange = &ldquo;fibonacci_sequence&rdquo;
  client.logger = Logger.new(STDOUT)
end</p>

<p>payload = { &ldquo;number&rdquo; => 10 }</p>

<p>response = rpc_client.publish(payload, &ldquo;fibonacci.route&rdquo;)
puts JSON.parse(response)[&ldquo;result&rdquo;]
```</p>

<p>Just don&rsquo;t forget to install RabbitMQ before ;).</p>

<p>And that&rsquo;s it! You will see the result of <code>55</code> getting printed. RPC with <code>bunny_borrow</code> merely requires binding to the right exchange, agreeing on the routing key we are going to use and publishing a message!</p>

<h3>Background jobs with Sneakers &ndash; Redis/Sidekiq replacement</h3>

<p>As already mentioned before, RabbitMQ can be a bit like Redis for background processing purposes. And it turns out that we even have a reliable replacement for Sidekiq that is backed by RabbitMQ! We can easily implement workers with <a href="https://github.com/jondot/sneakers">sneakers gem</a>, especially if you use ActiveJob as we have already adapter for Sneakers! But even if you use Sneakers standalone, you shouldn&rsquo;t expect too many surprises there. It looks like a regular worker class. The only difference is that it requires manual acknowledgment of having the message processed:</p>

<p>``` rb
class MySneakersWorker
  include Sneakers::Worker
  from_queue :queue_name</p>

<p>  def work(payload)</p>

<pre><code>Rails.logger.info "From Sneakers: #{payload}"

ack!
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>If you are curious why you might want to prefer Sneaker over Sidekiq, I would recommend reading the <a href="https://github.com/jondot/sneakers/wiki/Why-i-built-it">docs</a>.</p>

<h3>Event-Driven Applications with Hutch</h3>

<p>The case where RabbitMQ really will shine in our Rails applications is for event-driven architecture or in general, publish-subscribe use cases. It happens quite often in communication between microservices that we don&rsquo;t necessarily need synchronous calls between two or more apps and making it async will improve the efficiency, scalability and also will allow making the apps more independent, coherent and less coupled to each other. For example, if one application is down, we don&rsquo;t need to worry about this as our message will be processed eventually when the app is back. For synchronous flow, that would be very different as we would need to implement error handling and simply be prepared for that kind of scenario. Also, quite often, there is a clear distinction between primary logic behind some use cases and secondary logic.</p>

<p>Consider the following scenario: you have a checkout page in your e-commerce system where a user can enter credit card data and pay for the order. Are all the following &ldquo;features&rdquo; equally important?</p>

<ul>
<li>executing the charge and confirming the order</li>
<li>sending an email notification to the buyer</li>
<li>sending WhatsApp message someone who will be responsible for delivering this order</li>
<li>updating some internal stats about the orders</li>
</ul>


<p>The first one is clearly the critical part of the logic, and the rest looks like some extra aspects that happen after the order is paid. Should they be called from the same place? And how does it go with the Single Responsibility Principle?</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s visualize this scenario with the following pseudocode:</p>

<p>``` rb
class Order::ConfirmByPayment
  def call(order, payment)</p>

<pre><code>order.confirm!(payment)
send_notification_to_the buyer(order)
send_whatsapp_message_for_delivery(order)
update_stats_for_orders(order)
update_stats_for_payment(payment)
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  # private methods go here
end
```</p>

<p>Certainly, this class looks too busy as it is now. And what if we introduced some extra notifications or other aspects? Would we add just another private method? It doesn&rsquo;t sound exactly like something compliant with SRP.</p>

<p>So what options do we have? One way to deal with it is to go with publish-subscribe pattern &ndash; publish some domain event and implement subscribers that would react to this event. It is doable in Rails apps without too much hassle with <a href="https://github.com/krisleech/wisper">wisper</a> gem. Explaining how to use <code>wisper</code> is outside the scope of this article, but to cut a long story short, that&rsquo;s what this service would look like after a rewrite to event-driven architecture:</p>

<p>``` rb
class Order::ConfirmByPayment
  include Wisper::Publisher</p>

<p>  def call(order, payment)</p>

<pre><code>order.confirm!(payment)
broadcast(:order_confirmed_by_payment, order.as_json, payment.as_json)
</code></pre>

<p>  end
  # private methods go here
end
```</p>

<p>Each of the notification could be extracted to a separate class that is subscribed to <code>order_confirmed_by_payment</code> event. And that way, we would get clean and decoupled classes where the logic is easy to extend.</p>

<p>What does it have to do with RabbitMQ though?</p>

<p>In the code we&rsquo;ve just gone through, everything is implemented within the same application. However, this is not really necessary. Sending notifications can be async, and it&rsquo;s not needed to be done from the same application, we could have a separate service for stats, for sending email notifications, for sending WhatsApp messages etc. And for that, we need some simple way how to inform all the applications that they should do something. And that&rsquo;s where we will need RabbitMQ and one of the Ruby &ldquo;frameworks&rdquo; that is built for this kind of use cases.</p>

<h4>Building Example Producer and Consumer With RabbitMQ and Hutch</h4>

<p>We are going to use <a href="https://github.com/gocardless/hutch">hutch</a> gem to publish event <code>order.confirmed_by_payment</code> event so that some consumers (either within the same app or from apps, it doesn&rsquo;t make much difference) can do something upon it.</p>

<p>Hutch itself is quite opinionated, so there is not much left for us to figure out, yet, it&rsquo;s good to keep in mind that it uses <code>topic</code> exchanges.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s get back to our <code>Order::ConfirmByPayment</code> and publish a message with Hutch from there:</p>

<p>``` rb
class Order::ConfirmByPayment
  def call(order, payment)</p>

<pre><code>order.confirm!(payment)

Hutch.connect
Hutch::Config.set(:force_publisher_confirms, true)

Hutch.publish("order.confirmed_by_payment", payment: payment.as_json, order: order.as_json)
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>The logic is quite simple: first, we need to connect Hutch. That&rsquo;s probably not the place where it should be executed, some initializer might be a better idea, but it&rsquo;s in this class to keep the example simpler. It&rsquo;s the same thing with <code>force_publisher_confirms</code> option (that should be moved to some initializer as well) which we use here for extra durability and better guarantees as we require the publisher to wait for the confirmation that the message was published. And then, we publish our message with <code>payment</code> and <code>order</code> keys and their serialized projections as values under <code>order.confirmed_by_payment</code> routing key.</p>

<p>To consume the messages that are published by this class, we need some consumer classes:</p>

<p>``` rb
class Order::ConfirmedByPaymentStatsUpdaterConsumer
  include Hutch::Consumer
  consume &ldquo;order.confirmed_by_payment&rdquo;</p>

<p>  def process(message)</p>

<pre><code>do_something_with_payment_and_order(message.body[:payment], message.body[:order])
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>``` rb
class Order::ConfirmedByPaymentWhatsAppNotifierConsumer
  include Hutch::Consumer
  consume &ldquo;order.confirmed_by_payment&rdquo;</p>

<p>  def process(message)</p>

<pre><code>do_something_with_payment(message.body[:payment])
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>``` rb
class Order::ConfirmedByPaymentEmailNotifierConsumer
  include Hutch::Consumer
  consume &ldquo;order.confirmed_by_payment&rdquo;</p>

<p>  def process(message)</p>

<pre><code>do_something_with_order(message.body[:order])
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>And that&rsquo;s it! What we need to do is to define consumer classes that include <code>Hutch::Consumer</code> module, define the routing key under which we are going to consume messages and implement <code>process</code> method that will deal with the <code>message</code> that we get and do something with its <code>body</code> that contains what we published via publisher.</p>

<p>Optionally, we may want to specify <code>queue_name</code> explicitly, which is by default generated based on the class name. It will work without an explicit declaration for the majority of the cases, but what is going to happen if we have a consumer with the same class name in more than one application? Instead of having a publish-subscribe pattern, we are going to end up with competing consumers as having the same queue names is the way to do in RabbitMQ! In that case, it&rsquo;s worth prefixing queue name with the app&rsquo;s name or something else that would make it unique in your ecosystem:</p>

<p>``` rb
class Order::ConfirmedByPaymentWhatsAppNotifierConsumer
  include Hutch::Consumer
  consume &ldquo;order.confirmed_by_payment&rdquo;
  queue_name &ldquo;notifs_app_order_confirmed_by_payments_whats_app_notifier&rdquo;</p>

<p>  def process(message)</p>

<pre><code>do_something_with_payment(message.body[:payment])
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>The last thing to do is to start the worker process that will consume the messages:</p>

<p><code>
bundle exec hutch
</code></p>

<p>You should see an output that looks like this:</p>

<p><code>
2019-06-15T19:27:52Z 84284 INFO -- hutch booted with pid 84284
2019-06-15T19:27:52Z 84284 INFO -- found rails project (.), booting app in development environment
2019-06-15T19:27:57Z 84284 INFO -- connecting to rabbitmq (amqp://guest@127.0.0.1:5672/)
2019-06-15T19:27:57Z 84284 INFO -- connected to RabbitMQ at 127.0.0.1 as guest
2019-06-15T19:27:57Z 84284 INFO -- opening rabbitmq channel with pool size 1, abort on exception false
2019-06-15T19:27:57Z 84284 INFO -- using topic exchange 'hutch'
2019-06-15T19:27:57Z 84284 INFO -- HTTP API use is enabled
2019-06-15T19:27:57Z 84284 INFO -- connecting to rabbitmq HTTP API (http://guest@127.0.0.1:15672/)
2019-06-15T19:27:57Z 84284 INFO -- tracing is disabled
2019-06-15T19:27:57Z 84284 INFO -- setting up queues
</code></p>

<p>And you can enjoy using RabbitMQ in your apps and having the logic nicely decoupled with a little cost ;)</p>

<h2>Wrapping Up</h2>

<p><strong>RabbitMQ</strong> is an excellent choice if you need <strong>multiple applications</strong> to talk to each other via events instead of HTTP requests/responses and should you ever need <strong>synchronous</strong> calls, you could take advantage of its <strong>RPC</strong> capabilities. It&rsquo;s a mature <strong>message broker</strong> with well-established Ruby gems that will make it simple to introduce it in your Rails apps.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Messages on Rails Part 2: Kafka]]></title>
    <link href="https://karolgalanciak.com/blog/2019/04/07/messages-on-rails-part-2-kafka/"/>
    <updated>2019-04-07T20:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://karolgalanciak.com/blog/2019/04/07/messages-on-rails-part-2-kafka</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the <a href="https://karolgalanciak.com/blog/2019/02/24/messages-on-rails-part-1-introduction-to-kafka-and-rabbitmq/">first part</a> of this series, we were exploring some potential options for <strong>communication between services</strong> &ndash; what their advantages and disadvantages are, why <strong>HTTP API</strong> is not necessarily the best possible choice and suggesting that <strong>asynchronous messaging</strong> might be a better solution, using, e.g. <strong>RabbitMQ</strong> and <strong>Kafka</strong>. Let&rsquo;s focus this time entirely on the latter.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>What Is Kafka?</h2>

<p>Kafka is a distributed streaming platform which allows the implementation of a publish-subscribe model between producers and consumers. However, what is unique about Kafka, is the fact that it&rsquo;s somewhat closer to a storage system than a message queue. Unlike in a typical message queue, the messages are not removed once they are consumed, they are still kept there. But what exactly is that &ldquo;there&rdquo;? The events are stored in topics &ndash; the append-only logs in which messages are identified by &ldquo;offsets&rdquo;, which you could compare to array indexes. Topics can be split for parallelization by a specified key forming a partition.</p>

<p><img src="/images/messages_on_rails_part_2/kafka_topics.png" title="&lsquo;Kafka Topics&rsquo; &lsquo;Kafka Topics&rsquo;" ></p>

<p class="center">
  <a href="https://karolgalanciak.com/images/messages_on_rails_part_2/kafka_topics.png" target="_blank">See in better quality</a>
</p>


<p>What is more, a broker is not responsible for delivering the messages to the consumers &ndash; it is a responsibility of the consumer to make sure they consume the messages and keep track of the offsets so that they can read messages one by one.</p>

<p>There are notable side-effects of that design which gives a lot of options when it comes to taking advantage of Kafka. Since we deal with append-only logs, all the messages under a given partition in the topic are ordered. Also, as the messages are persistent and keeping track of the position in the log is on consumers, the events can be replayed by any consumer, including the new ones that have been just introduced to the ecosystem. When using a traditional message queue, there will be no way to access past messages when a new consumer joins, and you would need to do things like resending events manually or whatever else would make the most sense in that scenario, but with Kafka, this is something totally normal.</p>

<p>Since the messages are persisted, storage can become an issue on its own, What if our producers publish a massive number of events and we are not interested in keeping all of them, or we want to limit somehow the number of events that will be consumed by future consumers without actually losing anything important?</p>

<p>The first use case is quite simple &ndash; we may configure retention policy based on time (and, e.g., delete everything that is older than 30 days) or based on size (keep 1 TB of the logs). However, that might mean losing potentially valuable data.</p>

<p>That issue can be addressed differently, using log compaction. Imagine that you are publishing the projections of the models after each change to Kafka topics. If you are not interested in how exactly you ended up with having records in a particular state but only their latest state, there is clearly no need to store anything that happened before the last update. In that case, you can decide to compact logs by a given key achieving precisely that result. Moreover, you can also get rid of the message under a given key altogether &ndash; just send a message with the null payload for a specific key, and that&rsquo;s it! No issues with storage and no need to consume messages in the future to figure out in the end that some record was deleted and a lot of processing went for nothing.</p>

<h2>Modelling Kafka Topics</h2>

<p>It seems like modeling topics shouldn&rsquo;t be rocket science as we have limited options &ndash; we have topics where we can publish messages, and those topics can be parallelized by partitioning. However, this issue might be quite complex.</p>

<p>There are a couple of things that we need to take into consideration when designing topics:</p>

<ul>
<li>Messages are ordered within the same topic/partition</li>
<li>The more partitions we have, the higher the throughput we can achieve</li>
<li>The number of partitions per node has its limits which are determined by the number of file descriptors the operating system can handle since each partition is represented as a separate file. This value is configurable, yet, it is essential to keep that limit in mind and that you cannot increase it indefinitely, so having millions of partitions on a single node won&rsquo;t work</li>
<li>Also, more partitions increase latency</li>
<li>The number of topics is limited in the same way as the number of partitions. In that sense, 10 000 topics with a single partition will not be that different from 1 topic with 10 000 partitions</li>
</ul>


<p>A first idea that you might have in mind when designing topics is to have a topic per model, or generally speaking, a topic for events coming from the same model. That way, you might go with <code>orders</code> topic where you would publish events like <code>order_created</code>, <code>order_completed</code>, <code>order_canceled</code> etc.</p>

<p>There are several problems with that approach though. What if you have an event-driven system, where a consumer immediately acts on the data it receives? Let&rsquo;s say that you have invoicing microservice that sends invoices to customers upon <code>order_completed</code> events. Obviously, besides the data from orders, it requires the data from customers. What if a customer changes the shipping addresses just before the completion of the order (resulting in publishing <code>customer_shipping_address_updated</code> event), yet, the <code>order_completed</code> event was processed before since the messages are published to different topics and they get processed independently? It might be the case that the address on the invoice will be incorrect! You might protect yourself against this kind of issues by assuming eventual consistency and, e.g., not acting on <code>order_completed</code> immediately but waiting 5 minutes instead, but this is not a solution that will work in all the cases and sometimes the cost of having issues like that might be too big, and you just can&rsquo;t afford this.</p>

<p>In such case, if ordering matters, it is a better idea to publish events coming from different models to the same topic (and to the same partition!). In general, we can say that things that are needed together (order with their items and customer data) belong to the same topic/partition.</p>

<p>What if different consumers have different needs as far as ordering goes and what things should go together? It is a more tricky scenario, and there is no one-size-fits-all solution, you would need to make some tradeoffs, either on a producer or consumer(s) side.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s get back to our example and imagine that we have another service that is for some reason interested only in customers' data. Such an application would clearly be interested in <code>customer_shipping_address_updated</code> events, but they don&rsquo;t care at all about anything related to orders. That scenario is pretty simple as the solution might be just ignoring the events (i.e., doing nothing upon them) that the service is not interested in. However, what if that would mean ignoring 90% of the events from the topic? You may choose to publish the same kind of events to different topics, so that they are easier to consume by different consumers, so the extra overhead would be on the producer&rsquo;s side. There is a possibility of different scenario: another service has even more strict requirements about the ordering of more kinds of events. The solution would be no different though &ndash; either we could publish events to another topic, or we could use the same one and let the other consumers ignore even more events.</p>

<p>There is one more possible scenario: what if <code>order_completed</code> and <code>customer_shipping_address_updated</code> are a result of the same request/transaction? In such case, we could have a single event, e.g., <code>order_completed_with_customer_address_change</code> that would have a more complex payload and later, that event could be decomposed to smaller ones like <code>order_completed</code> and <code>customer_shipping_address_changed</code> and published to separate topics using a stream processor. Maybe this is a bit contrived scenario, yet, it&rsquo;s worth keeping in mind that decomposition of events may also be a viable option, which is a much better choice than publishing split events and trying to reconstruct the original one.</p>

<h2>Stream Processing With KSQL/Apache Spark/Apache Storm/Apache Samza/Apache Flink, oh my!</h2>

<p>Even if you are not deep into data science, you&rsquo;ve probably heard about Hadoop, which is arguably a king of batch processing in a big data world. However, that is not necessarily the most optimal solution if you need an almost real-time data processing which ideally requires working with streams (or at least with micro-batches). And this is exactly what we have with Kafka!  There is a wide range of tools that can work with Kafka easily that could be used for ETL (Extract, Transform, Load), Data Enrichment, Machine Learning, Interactive Analysis or even as an extra component of Event Sourcing (e.g., building projections of the models from all the streams of events). Depending on the use case and requirements (e.g. very low latency, ease of use), you could go with <a href="https://kafka.apache.org/documentation/streams/">Kafka Streams</a>, <a href="https://www.confluent.io/product/ksql/">KSQL</a>, <a href="https://spark.apache.org">Apache Spark</a>, <a href="http://storm.apache.org">Apache Storm</a>, <a href="http://samza.apache.org">Apache Samza</a>, <a href="https://flink.apache.org">Apache Flink</a> or yet another solution. The list is quite long, and each of these tools deserves a separate article which is out of the scope of this one. Yet, it&rsquo;s good to be aware of how introducing Kafka opens the way to more possibilities that are data-oriented.</p>

<h2>Building Example Producer and Consumer Apps With Karafka</h2>

<p>Now, time for some practice! Let&rsquo;s build an example producer/consumer app that produces and consumes some event. To keep the example simple, let&rsquo;s just build a single application as it will be no different than having a producer and consumer as separation applications.</p>

<p>We are going to use <a href="https://github.com/karafka/karafka">karafka</a> gem for that, which is a higher level framework that structures the way of producing and consuming events and allows to focus on the business logic instead of figuring out how to integrate Kafka with the rest of the application.</p>

<h3>Getting Started</h3>

<p>Let&rsquo;s generate a new application:</p>

<p><code>
rails new karafka_example
</code></p>

<p>And add required gems to Gemile:</p>

<p><code>rb
gem "waterdrop", git: "https://github.com/karafka/waterdrop.git", branch: "master"
gem "karafka", git: "https://github.com/karafka/karafka.git", branch: "master"
</code></p>

<p>Besides &ldquo;karafka&rdquo; gem, we also have &ldquo;waterdrop&rdquo; gem which is a dependency required for publishing events.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s run a generator for all the things we need from &ldquo;karafka&rdquo;:</p>

<p><code>
bundle exec karafka install
</code></p>

<p>That command should generate a couple of interesting files: <code>karafka.rb</code> in a root directory, <code>app/consumers</code> with <code>application_consumer.rb</code> file and <code>app/</code>responders directory with <code>application_responder.rb</code> file.</p>

<p>The first file is pretty much an initializer for Karafka application which is separated from Rails config and allows you to configure Karafka application and to draw routes, which is similar in terms of API as Rails application routes, but here, it&rsquo;s for topics and consumers.</p>

<p><code>ApplicationConsumer</code> class is what you would expect that class to be &ndash; a base class for consumers. The interface is quite straight-forward for basic use cases: we define <code>consume</code> instance method inside which we have available <code>params</code> or <code>params_batch</code> (if we enabled batch fetching for that topic) that give access to event&rsquo;s payload. There are also some callbacks available for consumers which you can check in the <a href="https://github.com/karafka/karafka/wiki/Consumer-callbacks">docs</a>.</p>

<p><code>ApplicationResponder</code> is a base class for producers. Why &ldquo;responder&rdquo; then and not a producer? Mostly due to the fact that they are quite similar to responders that you might have used in controllers as far as the intention goes. Usually, inside a responder, you declare a topic that you want to have registered so that you can send and consume events from it. Next, you define <code>respond</code> instance method which takes a single argument which is the event payload. From that method, you call <code>respond_with</code> method where you can provide topic name, a payload of the event and optionally, a partition key.</p>

<h3>Initializer</h3>

<p>Here&rsquo;s an initializer generated by <code>karafka</code> generator with some extra tweaks:</p>

<p>``` rb karafka.rb</p>

<h1>frozen_string_literal: true</h1>

<p>ENV[&lsquo;RAILS_ENV&rsquo;] ||= &lsquo;development&rsquo;
ENV[&lsquo;KARAFKA_ENV&rsquo;] = ENV[&lsquo;RAILS_ENV&rsquo;]
require ::File.expand_path(&lsquo;../config/environment&rsquo;, <strong>FILE</strong>)
Rails.application.eager_load!</p>

<h1>This lines will make Karafka print to stdout like puma or unicorn</h1>

<p>if Rails.env.development?
  Rails.logger.extend(</p>

<pre><code>ActiveSupport::Logger.broadcast(
  ActiveSupport::Logger.new($stdout)
)
</code></pre>

<p>  )
end</p>

<p>class KarafkaApp &lt; Karafka::App
  setup do |config|</p>

<pre><code>config.kafka.seed_brokers = %w[kafka://127.0.0.1:9092]
config.client_id = "karafka_example"
config.backend = :inline
config.batch_fetching = false
# Uncomment this for Rails app integration
# config.logger = Rails.logger
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  # Comment out this part if you are not using instrumentation and/or you are not
  # interested in logging events for certain environments. Since instrumentation
  # notifications add extra boilerplate if you want to achieve max performance,
  # listen to only what you really need for a given environment.
  Karafka.monitor.subscribe(Karafka::Instrumentation::StdoutListener)
  Karafka.monitor.subscribe(Karafka::Instrumentation::ProctitleListener)</p>

<p>  consumer_groups.draw do</p>

<pre><code>consumer_group :example do
  batch_fetching false

  topic :users do
    consumer UsersConsumer
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end</p>

<p>Karafka.monitor.subscribe(&lsquo;app.initialized&rsquo;) do
  # Put here all the things you want to do after the Karafka framework
  # initialization
end</p>

<p>KarafkaApp.boot!
```
The most interesting parts of that file are configuration and drawing the routes, so let&rsquo;s focus on them now.</p>

<p>In the configuration block, we need to specify URI for Kafka, which is going to be kafka://127.0.0.1:9092 by default (assuming that you have Kafka installed in the first place). We also need <code>client_id</code> to identify the app in Kafka and provide the proper namespace. Another option is specifying <code>backend</code> which we have set to be <code>inline</code>. It means that the processing of the events will happen in the karafka&rsquo;s workers, which might not be an optimal solution, especially for heavy processing. Alternatively, we can use Sidekiq thanks to <a href="https://github.com/karafka/sidekiq-backend">karafka sidekiq-backend gem</a>. Keep in mind though that with Sidekiq backend the the messages might no longer be processed in the order they arrived! For the sake of simplicity and the demonstration purposes, <code>batch_processing</code> is set to false. In such case, instead of dealing with a batch of messages (that would be available under <code>params_batch</code> method), we are going to have just <code>params</code> representing a single message.</p>

<p>In the next section, we are configuring the equivalent of routes for Kafka. We are registering <code>example</code> consumer group under which we specify that we want <code>UsersConsumer</code> class to be the consumer for <code>users</code> topic.</p>

<p>Consumers group is a concept that allows having competing consumers pattern for messages, which is useful if you don&rsquo;t want to have a publish-subscribe pattern with all consumers receiving the same message but only a single consumer processing the event.</p>

<p>There are a couple of more configuration options for topics that you can check in the <a href="https://github.com/karafka/karafka/wiki/Routing#topic-level-options">docs</a>.</p>

<h3>Building a producer</h3>

<p>Let&rsquo;s build the simplest possible producer that will merely take the payload and publish it to <code>users</code> topic:</p>

<p>``` rb app/responders/users_responder.rb
class UsersResponder &lt; ApplicationResponder
  topic :users</p>

<p>  def respond(event_payload)</p>

<pre><code>respond_to :users, event_payload
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<h3>Building a consumer</h3>

<p>And now, we can build a simple producer that will do nothing more than logging the params. As mentioned before, we have <code>params</code> method accessible on the instance level (or <code>params_batch</code> if batch fetching is enabled):</p>

<p>``` rb app/consumers/users_consumers.rb
class UsersConsumer &lt; ApplicationConsumer
  def consume</p>

<pre><code>Karafka.logger.info "New [User] event: #{params}"
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<h3>Seeing things in action</h3>

<p>Let&rsquo;s start the server process:</p>

<p><code>text
bundle exec karafka server
</code></p>

<p>If everything goes fine, you should see an output like this:
<code>text
I, [2019-04-07T10:30:41.517728 #83821]  INFO -- : Initializing Karafka server 83821
Karafka framework version: 1.3.0
Application client id: karafka_example
Backend: inline
Batch fetching: false
Batch consuming: false
Boot file: /path/to/app/karafka.rb
Environment: development
Kafka seed brokers: ["kafka://127.0.0.1:9092"]
I, [2019-04-07T10:30:41.602016 #83821]  INFO -- : Running Karafka server 83821
I, [2019-04-07T10:30:41.602870 #83821]  INFO -- : New topics added to target list: users
I, [2019-04-07T10:30:41.602948 #83821]  INFO -- : Fetching cluster metadata from kafka://127.0.0.1:9092
I, [2019-04-07T10:30:41.798673 #83821]  INFO -- : Discovered cluster metadata; nodes: your-machine-name.local:9092 (node_id=0)
I, [2019-04-07T10:30:41.798965 #83821]  INFO -- : [[karafka_example_example] {}:] Will fetch at most 1048576 bytes at a time per partition from users
I, [2019-04-07T10:30:41.799144 #83821]  INFO -- : [[karafka_example_example] {}:] Fetching cluster metadata from kafka://127.0.0.1:9092
I, [2019-04-07T10:30:41.799005 #83821]  INFO -- : [[karafka_example_example] {}:] Joining group `karafka_example_example`
I, [2019-04-07T10:30:41.801184 #83821]  INFO -- : [[karafka_example_example] {}:] Discovered cluster metadata; nodes: your-machine-name.local:9092 (node_id=0)
I, [2019-04-07T10:30:41.801287 #83821]  INFO -- : [[karafka_example_example] {}:] There are no partitions to fetch from, sleeping for 1s
I, [2019-04-07T10:30:42.047094 #83821]  INFO -- : [[karafka_example_example] {}:] Joined group `karafka_example_example` with member id `karafka_example-612b6612-26f1-41fe-95cd-49a52a6275c7`
I, [2019-04-07T10:30:42.047186 #83821]  INFO -- : [[karafka_example_example] {}:] Chosen as leader of group `karafka_example_example`
I, [2019-04-07T10:30:42.803209 #83821]  INFO -- : [[karafka_example_example] {}:] There are no partitions to fetch from, sleeping for 1s
I, [2019-04-07T10:30:43.050550 #83821]  INFO -- : [[karafka_example_example] {}:] Fetching cluster metadata from kafka://127.0.0.1:9092
I, [2019-04-07T10:30:43.052574 #83821]  INFO -- : [[karafka_example_example] {}:] Discovered cluster metadata; nodes: your-machine-name.local:9092 (node_id=0)
I, [2019-04-07T10:30:43.106051 #83821]  INFO -- : [[karafka_example_example] {}:] Partitions assigned for `users`: 0
I, [2019-04-07T10:30:43.805927 #83821]  INFO -- : [[karafka_example_example] {users: 0}:] Seeking users/0 to offset 0
I, [2019-04-07T10:30:43.806048 #83821]  INFO -- : [[karafka_example_example] {users: 0}:] New topics added to target list: users
I, [2019-04-07T10:30:43.806083 #83821]  INFO -- : [[karafka_example_example] {users: 0}:] Fetching cluster metadata from kafka://127.0.0.1:9092
I, [2019-04-07T10:30:43.807502 #83821]  INFO -- : [[karafka_example_example] {users: 0}:] Discovered cluster metadata; nodes: your-machine-name.local:9092 (node_id=0)
</code></p>

<p>And let&rsquo;s send some dummy event from the console using <code>UsersResponder</code>:</p>

<p><code>text
rails console
</code></p>

<p><code>rb
UsersResponder.call({ event_name: "user_created", payload: { id: 1 } })
</code></p>

<p>The output of that command should be similar to the following one:
<code>text
I, [2019-04-07T10:33:31.216585 #84497]  INFO -- : New topics added to target list: users
I, [2019-04-07T10:33:31.216940 #84497]  INFO -- : Fetching cluster metadata from kafka://localhost:9092
D, [2019-04-07T10:33:31.217337 #84497] DEBUG -- : [topic_metadata] Opening connection to localhost:9092 with client id delivery_boy...
D, [2019-04-07T10:33:31.220633 #84497] DEBUG -- : [topic_metadata] Sending topic_metadata API request 1 to localhost:9092
D, [2019-04-07T10:33:31.221051 #84497] DEBUG -- : [topic_metadata] Waiting for response 1 from localhost:9092
D, [2019-04-07T10:33:31.222211 #84497] DEBUG -- : [topic_metadata] Received response 1 from localhost:9092
I, [2019-04-07T10:33:31.222554 #84497]  INFO -- : Discovered cluster metadata; nodes: your-machine-name.local:9092 (node_id=0)
D, [2019-04-07T10:33:31.222818 #84497] DEBUG -- : Closing socket to localhost:9092
D, [2019-04-07T10:33:31.227719 #84497] DEBUG -- : Current leader for users/0 is node your-machine-name.local:9092 (node_id=0)
I, [2019-04-07T10:33:31.228077 #84497]  INFO -- : Sending 1 messages to your-machine-name.local:9092 (node_id=0)
D, [2019-04-07T10:33:31.228535 #84497] DEBUG -- : [produce] Opening connection to your-machine-name.local:9092 with client id delivery_boy...
D, [2019-04-07T10:33:31.445056 #84497] DEBUG -- : [produce] Sending produce API request 1 to your-machine-name.local:9092
D, [2019-04-07T10:33:31.452673 #84497] DEBUG -- : [produce] Waiting for response 1 from your-machine-name.local:9092
D, [2019-04-07T10:33:31.507604 #84497] DEBUG -- : [produce] Received response 1 from your-machine-name.local:9092
D, [2019-04-07T10:33:31.507995 #84497] DEBUG -- : Successfully appended 1 messages to users/0 on your-machine-name.local:9092 (node_id=0)
 =&gt; {"users"=&gt;[["{\"event_name\":\"user_created\",\"payload\":{\"id\":1}}", {:topic=&gt;"users"}]]}
</code></p>

<p>And if you check the logs of the karafka server, you will see that the message was successfully processed, including logging the message:</p>

<p><code>text
I, [2019-04-07T10:33:33.348308 #83821]  INFO -- : [[karafka_example_example] {}:] New [User] event: {"create_time"=&gt;2019-04-07 10:33:31 +0200, "headers"=&gt;{}, "is_control_record"=&gt;false, "key"=&gt;nil, "offset"=&gt;0, "deserializer"=&gt;#&lt;Karafka::Serialization::Json::Deserializer:0x00007fd463e96dc8&gt;, "partition"=&gt;0, "receive_time"=&gt;2019-04-07 10:33:33 +0200, "topic"=&gt;"users", "payload"=&gt;{"event_name"=&gt;"user_created", "payload"=&gt;{"id"=&gt;1}}, "deserialized"=&gt;true}
I, [2019-04-07T10:33:33.348375 #83821]  INFO -- : [[karafka_example_example] {}:] Inline processing of topic users with 1 messages took 9 ms
I, [2019-04-07T10:33:33.348410 #83821]  INFO -- : [[karafka_example_example] {}:] 1 message on users topic delegated to UsersConsumer
</code></p>

<p>And that&rsquo;s it! That&rsquo;s all that it takes to use Kafka in your Rails application.</p>

<h3>What about other features?</h3>

<p>We only used a tiny part of the framework, which turned out to be sufficient for the demonstration purposes. However, there are <a href="https://github.com/karafka/karafka/wiki">way more features</a> that would be worth getting familiar with before using <code>karafka</code> in your application.</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>Kafka is a <strong>great tool</strong> if you want a <strong>reliable</strong> and <strong>performant</strong> way of <strong>sending events between applications</strong> where a <strong>persistent storage</strong> for a certain amount of time and an ability of <strong>replaying events</strong> is essential and/or if you plan to do heavy <strong>stream-processing</strong>. Thanks to frameworks like <a href="https://github.com/karafka/karafka">karafka</a>, it&rsquo;s quite simple to start using Kafka in Rails applications.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Messages on Rails Part 1 -  Introduction to Kafka and RabbitMQ]]></title>
    <link href="https://karolgalanciak.com/blog/2019/02/24/messages-on-rails-part-1-introduction-to-kafka-and-rabbitmq/"/>
    <updated>2019-02-24T22:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://karolgalanciak.com/blog/2019/02/24/messages-on-rails-part-1-introduction-to-kafka-and-rabbitmq</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Microservices</strong>, <strong>Service-Oriented Architecture (SOA)</strong> and in general, <strong>distributed ecosystems</strong>, have been on hype in the last several years. And that&rsquo;s for a good reason! At certain point, The <strong>Majestic Monolith</strong> &ldquo;pattern&rdquo; might start causing issues, both from the purely technical reasons like scalability, tight coupling of the code if you don&rsquo;t follow <strong>Domain-Driven Design</strong> or some other practices <strong>improving modularity</strong>, maintenance overhead, and also from organizational perspective since working in smaller teams on smaller apps is more efficient than working with huge team on an even bigger monolith which suffers from tight coupling and low cohesion. However, this is only true if the overall architecture addresses the potential problems that are common in the micro/macro-services world. One of these problems I would like to focus on is communication between apps and how the data flows between them.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>How Can The Applications Talk To Each Other</h2>

<p>There are multiple ways the applications could talk to each other but let&rsquo;s focus on the most popular ones: shared database, HTTP API and messages.</p>

<h3>Shared Database</h3>

<p>It is arguable if we can talk about apps communicating with each other in this scenario; nevertheless, it&rsquo;s one of the ways to solve the problem of getting data from one application to another. And apart from some particular scenarios, it&rsquo;s the way that could give you a lot of headaches quite soon.</p>

<p>Initially, it might look like a great idea &ndash; you connect the other app to an existing database, and you don&rsquo;t need to worry about the communication! If the other application is just responsible for reading from that database, maybe you won&rsquo;t have any severe problems beyond increased load, issues of scaling and questionable access control (by default, the other app can do anything to that database). However, if you have multiple applications writing to the same database, you will undoubtedly have more serious issues &ndash; deadlocks, problems with data consistency as different constraints might apply to different applications, schema getting out of control with each application adding some custom tables and fields, which can turn out to be quite nasty &ndash; imagine one application acquiring Access Exclusive Lock on the entire table which turns out to be large (so the lock will not be released any time soon) thanks to some migration, while the other app was supposed to do some business-critical operations on that table that were also time-sensitive. Some of these problems are RDBMS-specific like locking during migration, but there is a very good chance anyway that you will be using either MySQL or PostgreSQL.</p>

<p>There are just too many things that can go wrong with having shared database that I would highly discourage from even trying that approach, maybe besides one single scenario &ndash; when what you need is exactly a replication of some data, e.g., to generate reports. In that case, you can set up PostgreSQL logical replication and let it replicate the data from the primary data source to a read-only replica containing only the data the application needs. Since PostgreSQL has a very reliable replication mechanism, you don&rsquo;t need to reinvent the wheel, and you can take advantage of that feature. Keep in mind that logical replication was introduced in PostgreSQL 10, so it&rsquo;s not available in the previous versions.</p>

<h3>HTTP API</h3>

<p>HTTP APIs, especially the RESTful APIs (although GraphQL has been getting quite popular in the last years), are arguably the most common blocks in microservices architecture as far as the communication between applications goes. REST architecture goes very well with HTTP, the communication between client and server is synchronous which makes it easy to reason about and debug, HTTP APIs are ubiquitous, and the developers are familiar with working with them. Also, HATEOAS and capabilities of getting precisely what you need from GraphQL make using with HTTP APIs easy, especially when working with Third-Party applications. Also, there is a lot of flexibility in implementing access control and authentication. On top of that, there are <a href="https://jsonapi.org">specifications</a> that clearly define how JSON APIs should be built, which minimizes reinventing the wheel and makes it even easier to build a client for that kind of API.</p>

<p>Based on those advantages it might look like communication between services via JSON APIs is the best possible solution to the problem, right?</p>

<p>Well, not necessarily. If you have one or two applications communicating with some other application, maybe it&rsquo;s not a bad idea, especially if the traffic is not huge and you don&rsquo;t need to transfer gigabytes of JSON daily via HTTP.</p>

<p>However, what if you expect a massive load from the services and indeed you will be transferring gigabytes of JSON via HTTP? Do you really need flexible authorization for communication between internal services? And why deal with an extra overhead of non-persistent connections and SSL handshakes in the first place?</p>

<p>Those things are great for integration with Third-Party applications, but they bring very little value in a closed ecosystem. Nevertheless, that overhead is not the biggest problem here, let&rsquo;s discuss something way more problematic: scaling.</p>

<p>Imagine that the API of one application is exposed to multiple other applications in your ecosystem. Also, the same application is used by &ldquo;real&rdquo; users who interact with it via UI. The immediate problem we have with that approach is that the traffic generated by the other services will be affecting regular users, which makes scaling decisions more tricky. To make it more complicated, let&rsquo;s say that in our example ecosystem we have a lot of data, and each application will be reading gigabytes of data every day and each service fetches data periodically from the API, e.g., every 5 minutes. To limit the number of requests so that we don&rsquo;t fetch the data that has been already fetched by the applications, we may want to implement some sort of data offset, which most likely will be based on the timestamp of the last fetch. We could send this timestamp that will filter out the records that haven&rsquo;t changed after that time and drastically reduce the number of requests that way. However, in a big enough scale, that will not be enough to solve all the issues. There can be thousands of records to be fetched every 5 minutes, which will most likely be paginated &ndash; that means a lot of requests. Multiply it by the number of applications and the traffic looks even more depressing, especially if every application will fetch exactly the same data.</p>

<p>Either the answer to the problem will be caching, which might be tricky to implement since the services will be using timestamp-based offset, or we can switch from pull-based strategy to push-based strategy.</p>

<p>A push-based strategy will be a publish-subscribe pattern via HTTP. The benefit of that is that we could serialize the state of the record after every change only once (or just serialize a changeset and go in the direction of CQRS/Event Sourcing) and send the payload to every service subscribed to a given event. The benefit of this approach is serializing a payload only once instead of doing it on every request, we can avoid useless requests which might happen if nothing has changed in the last 5 minutes and we could balance the load efficiently by moving the delivery logic to some background jobs. The disadvantage of publish-subscribe via HTTP, a.k.a. webhooks, would be implementing HTTP APIs in every service. Also, each application will experience massive traffic on a large enough scale.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s great if your ecosystem offers this kind of features for limiting the number of requests to Third-Party Applications, but is it the most efficient way of handling communication between internal applications and scaling the ecosystem?</p>

<p>This type of communication is arguably quite common in the microservices world, and the funny thing is that in some aspects it&rsquo;s no different than reimplementing messaging systems, but done in a less effective way.</p>

<p>There is a more efficient way to deal with the communication between internal services: using asynchronous messaging.</p>

<h3>Asynchronous Messaging</h3>

<p>Async messaging is a communication approach where a middleware, called message broker, connects producers of messages with consumers of those messages. Usually, a producer sends messages and the message broker is responsible for delivering them to proper consumers.</p>

<p>Thanks to having a message broker in-between the services, not only do we benefit from extra decoupling between the applications, but also we have way more flexibility as far as scalability goes.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s take a look at two very popular message brokers that take different approaches to messages: <a href="https://www.rabbitmq.com">RabbitMQ</a> and <a href="http://kafka.apache.org">Apache Kafka</a></p>

<h4>RabbitMQ</h4>

<p>RabbitMQ is a general purpose message broker supporting multiple protocols from which AMQP will be the one most interesting one to us. It implements a smart broker/dumb consumer model, which means the broker is responsible for delivering messages to the right place.</p>

<p>The essential design decision in RabbitMQ is that the producers shouldn&rsquo;t directly push messages to the queues, from which the consumers can read messages and process them. Instead, producers send messages to exchanges, and the queues are connected to these exchanges. That way, the producer doesn&rsquo;t know where exactly the message will be delivered and how many consumers are going to do anything with it if any! This kind of decoupling not only allows implementation of the publish-subscribe pattern, where multiple consumers using different queues bind to the same exchange and process the same message, but it also opens the way to quite a flexible routing (which we will cover in more details in the next part of this series). Once the consumer acknowledges the message, it is removed from the queue. Multiple producers can also subscribe to the same queue which will make them compete for the messages. The communication in a simple scenario as described above is illustrated in the following diagram:</p>

<p class="img-center-wrapper">
  <img class="img-center" src="/images/messages_on_rails_part_1/rabbitmq.png" title="RabbitMQ" alt="RabbitMQ">
</p>




<p class="center">
  <a href="https://karolgalanciak.com/images/messages_on_rails_part_1/rabbitmq.png" target="_blank">See in better quality</a>
</p>


<p>RabbitMQ is an excellent choice if you have complex routing scenarios, priority queues, you don&rsquo;t care about keeping messages in the queue after they are processed, and you don&rsquo;t expect an extreme throughput (although 100k messages/s that you can get in some <a href="https://www.cloudamqp.com/plans.html">RabbitMQ As A Service solutions</a>, even in a high availability scenario, is in most cases more than enough).</p>

<h4>Kafka</h4>

<p>Kafka is a distributed streaming platform which takes a different approach than RabbitMQ &ndash; it implements a dumb broker/smart consumer model. In that case,  it is the responsibility of the consumers to fetch messages and keep track of their state. What is unique about Kafka is the fact that it is not a message queue &ndash; it is an append-only log. Producers send messages to the topics, to which consumers subscribe and read the messages and keep the offset which is the information about the position in the log until which the messages were read. It can be illustrated the following way:</p>

<p><img src="/images/messages_on_rails_part_1/kafka.png" title="&lsquo;Kafka&rsquo; &lsquo;Kafka&rsquo;" ></p>

<p class="center">
  <a href="https://karolgalanciak.com/images/messages_on_rails_part_1/kafka.png" target="_blank">See in better quality</a>
</p>


<p>Such a design opens a way to some interesting features. The log is persistent with configurable retention which can be based on the size or time how long the events should be kept in the log, which makes Kafka act like a circular buffer. To save some space, Kafka allows log compaction when the messages are sent with the same key, keeping only the last one as a result. If storage is not an issue, you might even decide never to delete any messages!</p>

<p>On top of that, Kafka can easily handle a massive throughput &ndash; 100 000 messages/second is not extraordinary, it&rsquo;s easy to scale, and there are <a href="https://events.static.linuxfound.org/sites/events/files/slides/Kafka%20At%20Scale.pdf">cases</a> of handling millions of messages per second.</p>

<p>A persistent log is a killer-feature of Kafka. When you add another service to your ecosystem and need to get the data from one app to another, you will run into obvious issues when using a traditional message queue since the messages are gone after they are processed. With Kafka, just can add a new consumer and replay all the past events! You can also combine Kafka with stream processing frameworks like <a href="http://samza.apache.org">Apache Samza</a>, <a href="http://spark.apache.org">Apache Spark</a>, <a href="http://storm.apache.org">Apache Storm</a>,<a href="https://www.confluent.io/product/ksql/">KSQL</a> or use Kafka Streams.</p>

<p>Kafka is an excellent choice for use cases where the routing is not complex, the throughput is substantial, the messages need to stay in the log (even indefinitely) and where you expect the need to replay messages. You can also do Event Sourcing with Kafka and use stream processor like Kafka Stream or KSQL to construct projections from the events.</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p><strong>Communication</strong> between multiple services in a <strong>distributed ecosystem</strong> is far from a trivial problem, which can be approached in various ways: via a <strong>shared database</strong> (although to a very limited extent), <strong>HTTP APIs</strong> or <strong>messages</strong>.</p>

<p>In the next parts I&rsquo;ll be focusing on <strong>Kafka</strong> and <strong>RabbitMQ</strong> &ndash; how they work and how to use them in Rails applications, how to produce and consume messages, what kind of extra options you get by introducing Kafka and RabbitMQ to your ecosystem, potential issues you might have in some specific scenarios and show some examples where combining both could bring benefits.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Problems With Validating ActiveRecord Models And Why State Validation Is a Bad Idea]]></title>
    <link href="https://karolgalanciak.com/blog/2018/09/30/the-problems-with-validating-activerecord-models-and-why-state-validation-is-a-bad-idea/"/>
    <updated>2018-09-30T20:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://karolgalanciak.com/blog/2018/09/30/the-problems-with-validating-activerecord-models-and-why-state-validation-is-a-bad-idea</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the typical <strong>Rails application</strong>, you can find the most of the validations in the <strong>ActiveRecord models</strong>, which is nothing surprising &ndash; ActiveRecord models are used for multiple things. Whether it is a good thing, or a bad thing (in most cases it&rsquo;s the latter) deserves a separate book or at least blog post-series as it&rsquo;s not a simple problem, there is one specific thing that can cause <strong>a lot of issues</strong> that are <strong>difficult to solve</strong> and go beyond <strong>design decisions</strong> and ease of maintenance of the application, something that impacts the behavior of the model &ndash; <strong>the validations</strong>.</p>

<p>Just to give you a real-world example of what validation in ActiveRecord model looks like (as impossible as it seems, it really did happen) &ndash; when updating the check-in time of the reservation, which is a simple attribute on Reservation model, the record turned out to be invalid because&hellip; the format of guest&rsquo;s phone didn&rsquo;t match some regexp.</p>

<p>There are multiple ways to bypass this problem: use <code>validate: false</code> flag with <code>save</code> method: <code>save(validate: false)</code> or use <code>update_columns</code> method, but this is definitely not something that can be applied in a &ldquo;normal&rdquo; use case. In a typical scenario, this will be the error message displayed in the UI/returned to API consumer, and it will be confusing.</p>

<p>However, this is the expected behavior of ActiveRecord (or in general, ActiveModel-style) validations, which is <strong>a validation of the state</strong> of the model. And judging from this example, it&rsquo;s evident that it leads to <strong>problematic scenarios</strong>. What kind of design then would be the most appropriate to <strong>prevent such issues</strong>?</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Forget State Validation</h2>

<p>Based on the previous example, it&rsquo;s clear that the real problem is the idea of a model&rsquo;s state validation. And the more complex state of the models can be (especially if there are some cross-validations between several models, which is not uncommon in complex applications), the more problems you will get.</p>

<p>Just wanted to update some <code>notes</code> attribute to add some quick info about something? Forget it &ndash; you will get three different validation errors that will tell you that someone&rsquo;s email has an invalid format, description is too short, a discount amount of something is invalid.</p>

<p>Sadly, this is the typical Rails Way of handling validations. In the initial phase of the application, this is certainly convenient &ndash; adding new validations is super easy, there is no need to discuss the design of potential alternatives and how it fits the bigger picture, and there is very little overhead. Unless you are ok with such problems, at some point, you will probably need to migrate validations to some other solution. What would be the potential alternative for validations?</p>

<h2>Validate The Actual Use Case</h2>

<p>The answer to that question is straight-forward (although it doesn&rsquo;t mean that achieving it will be simple) &ndash; just validate the thing you are doing, the actual use case. If you want to update <code>description</code>, you should only be concerned with the description &ndash; if it&rsquo;s present or not, it&rsquo;s length, etc., whether <code>headline</code> is too short or not (this can happen when you change the validation rules and don&rsquo;t somehow migrate the data) is not the subject of that use case.</p>

<p>There are a lot of implications of such approach &ndash; indeed, it will result in different sets of validators per creation and per update, since for creation we usually need way more data, and for an update, we may merely want to update a single attribute. Effectively, it will result in different validation pipelines for create and update actions. For creating, we may always need to apply specific validators (e.g., presence validators for some attributes), but for updating it will make more sense to apply only the validators for what we are trying to do &ndash; when we want to update email, we apply the presence and format validation for an email, if we want to update a description, we apply presence and length validators for a description.</p>

<h2>Potential Implementation</h2>

<p>What would be the way to implement it? The specific design is out of the scope of this article as it might require building mini-framework for validations and consider some design implications on the entire application (especially if we are escaping the traditional Rails Way). However, one thing is sure here &ndash; there will be dedicated validator objects, probably different for create and update action, and the validations will need to be removed from ActiveRecord models.</p>

<p>A potential way of interacting with such objects could look like this:</p>

<p><code>rb
validation_result = Reservation::CreateValidator.call(params)
if validation_result.success?
  # handle happy path here
else
  puts validation_result.errors.messages # for convenience and familiarity, `errors` object could have a similar interface to ActiveModel::Errors
end
</code></p>

<p>What if we need the model itself in the validator due to some complex business rules, like cross-model validation? We could either reuse <code>id</code> from <code>params</code> or just provide <code>model</code> as an argument:</p>

<p><code>rb
validation_result = Reservation::CreateValidator.call(record, params)
</code></p>

<h2>Side-Effects Of Such Design</h2>

<p>The implications of such design go far deeper than just moving things from one place to another to prevent some edge cases (and naturally increasing the complexity of the design, but it seems to be a fair price to pay for what we get as a result). Since it would make the most sense to have validations per use case, then&hellip; maybe we can have use case as objects that would expose their constraints, and the validators would take the rules from those objects and apply some specific logic on top of it to achieve the desired result? Maybe we could even create value objects composed of a single or multiple attributes, e.g. <code>Client::Email</code> object that would enforce its constraints and also, move some logic specific to the email itself in the context of a hypothetical <code>Client</code> model? And if we can identify the use cases themselves, aren&rsquo;t they domain events? And how hard would it be to build event-based architecture, or even apply Event Sourcing?</p>

<p>These are not trivial questions, however, doing one change in the design opens
the door to a holistic architectural approach where all parts of the domain fit together and the interaction between them is way more intentional comparing to ad hoc duct-tape-like solutions.</p>

<h2>Wrapping Up</h2>

<p>Putting <strong>too much logic</strong> in <strong>ActiveRecord models</strong> has a lot of disadvantages, most of them being problematic on the <strong>design level</strong>. However, things like validations can result in some nasty issues that go beyond the maintenance and cause actual business problems. Fortunately, by keeping that in mind and putting the <strong>validation logic</strong> in a <strong>separate object(s)</strong>, we can easily avoid such issues and as a nice side-effect, have a design that is way more flexible, extendible and eventually simpler to maintain.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Indexes on Rails: How to make the most of your Postgres database]]></title>
    <link href="https://karolgalanciak.com/blog/2018/08/19/indexes-on-rails-how-to-make-the-most-of-your-postgres-database/"/>
    <updated>2018-08-19T20:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://karolgalanciak.com/blog/2018/08/19/indexes-on-rails-how-to-make-the-most-of-your-postgres-database</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Optimizing <strong>database queries</strong> is arguably one of the fastest ways to improve the <strong>performance</strong> of the Rails applications. There are multiple ways how you can approach it, depending on the kind of a problem. <strong>N+1 queries</strong> seem to be a pretty common issue, which is, fortunately, <strong>easy to address</strong>. However, sometimes you have some relatively <strong>simple-looking queries</strong> that seem to take way longer than they should be, indicating that they might require some optimization. The best way to improve such queries is adding a <strong>proper index</strong>.</p>

<p>But what does &ldquo;proper index&rdquo; mean? How to figure out what kind of index is exactly needed for a given query? Here are some essential facts and tips that should cover a majority of the queries you may encounter and make your database no longer a bottleneck.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Why index at all?</h2>

<p>Simple &ndash; to have faster queries. But why are indexes faster? The alternative to index is a sequential scanning of the entire table. That might not sound like a bad idea, but imagine you are performing a search over a huge table. What would be the fastest way to retrieve all records you are looking for &ndash; by scanning the entire table, or maybe having a way to store a subset of the records, based on some specific criteria, and then retrieve them from that place? Obviously, it&rsquo;s the second option. And that&rsquo;s roughly how indexes work.</p>

<p>As trivial as it sounds, there is a valuable lesson to learn from it: to achieve a good performance, the index must be selective enough. And the more specific you will be about those criteria, the better.</p>

<h2>Index Types</h2>

<p>Although Postgres by defaults creates <code>B-Tree</code> index when using <code>CREATE INDEX</code> command, there are a couple of more indexes that will be certainly useful in many use cases. Let&rsquo;s check them all out:</p>

<h3>B-Tree Index</h3>

<p><code>B-Tree</code> is a self-balancing tree data structure which keeps data ordered and easy to search. This index is appropriate for equality and range queries (using operators like <code>&gt;=</code>,  <code>&lt;</code> etc.) and will work great with text, timestamp and number fields.</p>

<p>B-Tree indexes are a reasonable default for most of the queries, but not for all of them. The limitation comes from the underlying structure. Discussing the details of the B-Tree data structure itself is beyond the scope of this article; nevertheless, it&rsquo;s worth keeping in mind that it&rsquo;s a similar data structure to a binary search tree, which has meaningful consequences on what can be indexed with it and how. We will get back to a couple of examples later.</p>

<h3>Hash Index</h3>

<p>Before Postgres 10, the usage of hash indexes was discouraged since they used to be not WAL-logged. Fortunately, it&rsquo;s changed in Postgres 10, and we can use them safely without worrying about rebuilding the index if something goes wrong with our database that would cause a crash. The use cases where hash indexes are useful are very limited, as they work only for equality, but they are a bit more efficient for this kind of queries comparing to b-tree indexes. If you store tokens for example and perform lookups by the token value, hash indexes would be a good way to optimize such queries.</p>

<h3>BRIN Index (Block Range Index)</h3>

<p>BRIN indexes were introduced in Postgres 9.5 which make them a pretty new addition. They tend to work very well for the large sets of ordered data, e.g., statistical data collected with timestamps which are later filtered by the time range. They will perform better than b-tree indexes in such case, although the difference won&rsquo;t be drastic. However, the different of the size of the index will be huge &ndash; BRIN index can be smaller by literally few orders of magnitude comparing to b-tree index.</p>

<h3>GIN Index (Generalized Inverted Index)</h3>

<p>GIN Indexes are the perfect choice for &ldquo;composite values&rdquo; where you perform a query which looks for an element within such &ldquo;composite&rdquo;. That is the index you will most likely want to use for <code>jsonb</code>, <code>array</code> or <code>hstore</code> data structures. They are also an excellent choice for full-text search.</p>

<h3>GiST Index (Generalized Inverted Seach Tree Index)</h3>

<p>GiST Indexes will be a good choice when the records overlap values under the same column. They are commonly used for geometry types and full-text search as well. The difference between GIN and GiST Index when it comes to full-text search is that GiST Index will be less taxing on writes comparing to GIN (as it is faster to build). But since it&rsquo;s a lossy index, there might be some extra overhead involved for reads, which makes GIN index a better choice when you mostly care about reads optimization.</p>

<h2>Optimizing Queries</h2>

<p>Here are some tips that should help you with the majority of the queries:</p>

<h3>Start with EXPLAIN</h3>

<p>With enough experience and knowledge of your app, you will develop an intuition about indexes and where they might be useful, long before having performance problems with queries. Until that happens, it&rsquo;s essential to understand how Postgres is going to execute these queries. The best tool for that purpose is using <code>EXPLAIN</code> command, which will show the execution plan generated by the query planner. <code>ActiveRecord</code> provides a convenient method &ndash; <code>explain</code> &ndash; that you can use on collections to get the query plan:</p>

<p>```</p>

<blockquote><p>Order.where(customer_id: 1).explain
  Order Load (13.8ms)  SELECT &ldquo;orders&rdquo;.<em> FROM &ldquo;orders&rdquo; WHERE &ldquo;orders&rdquo;.&ldquo;customer_id&rdquo; = $1  [[&ldquo;customer_id&rdquo;, 1]]
=> EXPLAIN for: SELECT &ldquo;orders&rdquo;.</em> FROM &ldquo;orders&rdquo; WHERE &ldquo;orders&rdquo;.&ldquo;customer_id&rdquo; = $1 [[&ldquo;customer_id&rdquo;, 1]]</p>

<pre><code>                                       QUERY PLAN
</code></pre>

<hr />

<p> Index Scan using index_orders_on_customer_id on orders  (cost=0.15..19.62 rows=50 width=1417)
   Index Cond: (customer_id = 1)
(2 rows)
```</p></blockquote>

<p>Unfortunately, <code>EXPLAIN ANALYZE</code>, which provides even more insight, as it performs a real query, is not supported out of the box by ActiveRecord. However, it can be added using an extra gem. You can check out <a href="https://pawelurbanek.com/slow-rails-queries">this blog post</a> to learn more about it.</p>

<h3>How to tell a good query plan from a bad one?</h3>

<p>This is not that simple as it sounds, as the sequential scan can be sometimes more efficient than using an index, especially if not kept in memory, but stored entirely on disk, and even worse, an HDD one. Usually, a preferable query plan is the one that looks simpler and utilizes the least possible number of indexes, which means that it&rsquo;s better to use one index instead of two of them, like in the following example:</p>

<p>```</p>

<blockquote><p>Product.where(warehouse_id: 1).where(category_id: 1).explain
  Product Load (0.5ms)  SELECT &ldquo;products&rdquo;.<em> FROM &ldquo;products&rdquo; WHERE &ldquo;products&rdquo;.&ldquo;warehouse_id&rdquo; = $1 AND &ldquo;products&rdquo;.&ldquo;category_id&rdquo; = $2  [[&ldquo;warehouse_id&rdquo;, 1], [&ldquo;category_id&rdquo;, 1]]
=> EXPLAIN for: SELECT &ldquo;products&rdquo;.</em> FROM &ldquo;products&rdquo; WHERE &ldquo;products&rdquo;.&ldquo;warehouse_id&rdquo; = $1 AND &ldquo;products&rdquo;.&ldquo;category_id&rdquo; = $2 [[&ldquo;warehouse_id&rdquo;, 1], [&ldquo;category_id&rdquo;, 1]]</p>

<pre><code>                                                   QUERY PLAN
</code></pre>

<hr />

<p> Bitmap Heap Scan on products  (cost=9.08..13.10 rows=1 width=1417)
   Recheck Cond: ((warehouse_id = 1) AND (category_id = 1))
   &ndash;>  BitmapAnd  (cost=9.08..9.08 rows=1 width=0)</p>

<pre><code>     -&gt;  Bitmap Index Scan on index_products_on_warehouse_id_and_name_and_something_else  (cost=0.00..4.31 rows=5 width=0)
           Index Cond: (warehouse_id = 1)
     -&gt;  Bitmap Index Scan on index_products_on_category_id  (cost=0.00..4.52 rows=50 width=0)
           Index Cond: (category_id = 1)
</code></pre>

<p>(7 rows)
```</p></blockquote>

<p>It doesn&rsquo;t necessarily mean that this query plan is a bad one &ndash; it could be totally the case that such query is fast enough. However, if read speed is more important for us than the index size and extra overhead on writes which will make them slower, the best way to deal with such query would be adding a compound index on both <code>warehouse_id</code> and <code>category_id</code>.</p>

<p>One statement that is especially worth keeping an eye on (besides <code>Seq Scan</code> which stands for a sequential scan) is <code>Filter</code> statement which indicates that the records required extra filtering and the index was not enough. Here is one example:</p>

<p><code>
 Index Scan using index_products_on_category_id on products
   Index Cond: (category = 1)
   Filter: (created_at = '2018-08-11'::date)
</code></p>

<p>Ideally, <code>created_at</code> part would appear in <code>Index Cond</code> and be fully covered by the index. Usually, adding a compound index on multiple columns solves the issue which in this example would mean having an index on both <code>category_id</code> and <code>created_at</code>, not only on <code>category_id</code>.</p>

<h3>Sequence of the columns in B-Tree index does matter</h3>

<p>The sequence of the columns in a multi-column index is critical. Imagine that you created a following index: <code>create_index :tag_items, [:taggable_type, :taggable_id]</code> and want to perform a couple of queries. For sure this index is going to be efficient for searching by both <code>taggable_type</code> and <code>taggable_id</code>. It will also work great for search by <code>taggable_type</code>. It won&rsquo;t, however, be efficient when performing a search just by <code>taggable_id</code>. The reason why it is like that is quite simple though &ndash; try to imagine how the data would be stored in a hypothetical B-Tree. First, the nodes will be organized based on the leftmost column and then, by another one. Traversing such tree when you do a search based on <code>taggable_type</code> or both <code>taggable_type</code> and <code>taggable_id</code> will be simple. However, you can&rsquo;t do the same with just <code>taggable_id</code>. Postgres might use this index anyway as it might turn out to be still more efficient than a sequential scan, but this is going to be suboptimal. If it happens that you need to perform queries by <code>taggable_id</code> only, it would be a good idea to add a separate index on that field.</p>

<h3>Unique Indexes</h3>

<p>The biggest need behind unique indexes is ensuring data integrity (since most uniqueness validations, including ActiveRecord one, don&rsquo;t enforce anything and are more useful for having a nice error message and not raising an exception than for data integrity). However, a nice side effect of a unique index is also a better performance comparing to a non-unique one.</p>

<h3>Partial Indexes</h3>

<p>Imagine that you have some Articles in your application and you want to add <code>published_at</code> datetime field indicating whether and when the article was published, and then, filter published articles by a given author. We can most likely expect a need for an index on <code>author_id</code> column in such case. What about our second condition? We could for sure add a compound index on both <code>author_id</code> and <code>published_at</code>. However, there is a better choice. We could add a partial index for <code>author_id</code> which covers only published articles, i.e., covers <code>WHERE published_at IS NOT NULL</code>!</p>

<p>Fortunately, this is supported by Rails (although writing a SQL command wouldn&rsquo;t be that difficult), we just need to use <code>where</code> option for that:</p>

<p><code>rb
add_index :articles, :author_id, where: "published_at IS NOT NULL"
</code></p>

<h3>Expression Indexes</h3>

<p>Imagine that you need to search users by their first name which comes from some input provided by a user. However, to avoid issues with figuring out whether the name provided by a user starts with a capital letter or not or how the names were stored in the database in the first place, you perform a query like this:</p>

<p><code>rb
User.where("lower(first_name) = ?", name.downcase)
</code></p>

<p>This query will obviously work, however, if you have a lot of users, a query plan will indicate that it is suboptimal and instead of seeing something like <code>Index Scan using index_users_on_first_name on users</code>, you will see <code>Seq Scan on users</code>.</p>

<p>There is no need to worry though. Postgres allows creating expression indexes where you can apply some functions, which in our case is <code>lower</code>. A proper index for this scenario would need to be created that way:</p>

<p><code>rb
add_index :users, "lower(first_name)", name: "index_users_on_lower_first_name"
</code></p>

<h3>Optimizing LIKE queries</h3>

<p>Optimizing queries with <code>LIKE</code> clause is simple; you just need to remember about two things:</p>

<ol>
<li>Forget about B-Tree Index for this case.</li>
<li>Take advantage of trigram matching provided by <a href="https://www.postgresql.org/docs/10/static/pgtrgm.html">pg_trgm</a> extension.</li>
</ol>


<p>To avoid sequential scans and utilize index that will drastically improve the performance of this kind of queries, enable the extension and create a GIN or GiST index:</p>

<p><code>
execute "CREATE EXTENSION pg_trgm;"
execute "CREATE INDEX CONCURRENTLY index_products_on_description_trigram ON clients USING gin(description gin_trgm_ops);"
</code></p>

<p>Thanks to this index, this is a query plan you might expect when filtering <code>Products</code> by <code>descriptions</code> containing some text, with wildcards on both the beginning and the end:</p>

<p>```
EXPLAIN for: SELECT &ldquo;products&rdquo;.* FROM &ldquo;products&rdquo; WHERE (products.description ILIKE &lsquo;%some text with wildacards%&rsquo;)</p>

<pre><code>                                            QUERY PLAN
</code></pre>

<hr />

<p> Bitmap Heap Scan on products
   Recheck Cond: (description ~~* &lsquo;%some text with wildacards%&rsquo;::text)
   &ndash;>  Bitmap Index Scan on index_products_on_description_trigram</p>

<pre><code>     Index Cond: (description ~~* '%some text with wildacards%'::text)
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<h3>Ordering</h3>

<p>B-tree indexes are sorted in an ascending order which we can use to our advantage to avoid performing sorting in memory. However, we also need to keep in mind the limitation of the data structure itself. A rule of thumb for efficient ordering would be: order by the same columns you perform filtering by. It is going to be the case by default when you don&rsquo;t explicitly add any <code>ORDER</code> clause since the indexes are ordered. But if it happens that you need to apply different ordering criteria, you can take advantage of <code>order</code> option and explicitly specify the order:</p>

<p><code>
add_index :products, :created_at, order: { created_at: :desc }
</code></p>

<h3>Adding indexes concurrently</h3>

<p>The way how the indexes are added doesn&rsquo;t impact the performance once they are created; however, it&rsquo;s good to keep in mind that just simple <code>CREATE INDEX</code> will block concurrent writes (inserts, updates, and deletes) until it&rsquo;s finished. It can lead to some issues, including deadlocks, especially when the index is getting created for a huge table under massive write operations.</p>

<p>To prevent such a problem, it&rsquo;s worth creating indexes <a href="https://www.postgresql.org/docs/10/static/sql-createindex.html#SQL-CREATEINDEX-CONCURRENTLY">concurrently</a> instead. You can do that in Rails using <code>algorithm: :concurrently</code> option and by making sure that the index creation will run outside of a transaction by calling <code>disable_ddl_transaction!</code>.</p>

<p>``` rb
class AddIndexToAsksActive &lt; ActiveRecord::Migration[5.0]
  disable_ddl_transaction!</p>

<p>  def change</p>

<pre><code>add_index :users, :active, algorithm: :concurrently
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>There is one caveat here though. If you attempt to create a unique index concurrently, there is a possibility that something will go wrong, e.g., when a non-unique record is created during the index creation. Since the command is run outside the transaction, it won&rsquo;t be rolled back, and you will end up with an invalid index. Nevertheless, that is not a big problem &ndash; should it ever happen, just drop the invalid index and try creating it concurrently one more time.</p>

<h2>Wrapping up</h2>

<p>Optimizing <strong>PostgreSQL queries</strong> might not look a trivial task, but if you keep these rules in mind, you will have much easier time with your database, and you will enjoy fast queries for a long time.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
