<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ECMAScript | Karol Galanciak - Ruby on Rails and Ember.js consultant]]></title>
  <link href="https://karolgalanciak.com/blog/categories/ecmascript/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://karolgalanciak.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-06-12T17:32:38+02:00</updated>
  <id>https://karolgalanciak.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Karol Galanciak]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[JavaScript: The Surprising Parts]]></title>
    <link href="https://karolgalanciak.com/blog/2017/01/22/javascript-the-surprising-parts/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-22T22:45:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://karolgalanciak.com/blog/2017/01/22/javascript-the-surprising-parts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Do you think you know all the surprising parts of <strong>JavaScript</strong>? Some of these "features" may look as if the language was broken, but it's not necessarily the case. Things like <strong>variables hoisting</strong>, <strong>variables scope</strong>, behaviour of <code>this</code> are quite intentional and besides just being different from most of other programming languages, there is nothing particularly wrong with them. However, there are still some things that are quite surprising about <strong>JavaScript</strong>. Let's take a look at some of them.</p>




<!--more-->




<h2>Surprise #1 - <code>parseInt</code> function</h2>




<p>Imagine you have some numbers as strings and you want to convert them to integers. You could probably use <code>Number()</code> function to do that, but let's assume you are used to <code>parseInt()</code> function. Let's do some conversions then:</p>


<p>``` js
[&ldquo;1&rdquo;].map(parseInt);
// [1]</p>

<p>[&ldquo;1&rdquo;, 2, &ldquo;3&rdquo;, 4].map(parseInt);
// => [1, NaN, NaN, NaN] // WUT ?!</p>

<p>[&ldquo;1&rdquo;, 2, &ldquo;3&rdquo;, 4].map(parseFloat);
// => [1, 2, 3, 4] // WUT&hellip;
```</p>

<p>Something is definitely wrong here. How could possibly <code>parseFloat()</code> work fine here and <code>parseInt()</code> not? Obviously <strong>JavaScript</strong> is broken, right?</p>




<p>Not really. This is actually the expected behaviour. The difference between <code>parseFloat</code> and <code>parseInt()</code> is that <code>parseFloat()</code> takes only one argument (<code>string</code>), but <code>parseInt()</code>takes two arguments - <code>string</code> and... <code>radix</code>. To verify it, let's rewrite the mapping using an anonymous function:</p>


<p><code>js
["1", 2, "3", 4].map((number) =&gt; parseInt(number));
// =&gt; [1, 2, 3, 4]
</code></p>

<p>When you pass simply <code>parseInt()</code> function as an argument to <code>map()</code>, the second argument (which is a current index) is going to be passed as <code>radix</code> to <code>parseInt</code>, which explains why it returns <code>NaN</code>. The equivalent of just passing <code>parseInt</code> looks like this:</p>


<p><code>js
["1", 2, "3", 4].map((number, index, array) =&gt; parseInt(number, index, array));
</code></p>

<p>As "odd" as it may look like, this is a perfectly valid behaviour and there is nothing wrong with <code>JavaScript</code> ;).</p>




<h2>Surprise #2 - sorting</h2>




<p>Now that we've learned how to parse integers in <strong>JavaScript</strong> like a boss, let's do some sorting:</p>


<p><code>js
[1, 20, 2, 100].sort();
// =&gt; [1, 100, 2, 20] // WUT again...
</code></p>

<p>Again, something odd is going on here. However, this is the intended behavior - after consulting with <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en/docs/Web/JavaScript/Reference/Global_Objects/Array/sort" target="_blank">docs</a>, we can learn that <code>sort()</code> converts all elements into strings and compares them in Unicode code point order. I think this might be a big surprise for a majority of developers performing sorting and seeing the result, but this behaviour is clearly documented. Due to the necessity of maintaing backwards compatibility, I wouldn't expect this behavior to change, so it's worth keeping it in mind.</p>




<p>To perform sorting on integers you need to provide a <strong>compare function</strong>:</p>


<p><code>js
[1, 20, 2, 100].sort((a, b) =&gt; a - b);
// =&gt; [1, 2, 20, 100]
</code></p>

<h2>Surprise #3 - <code>==</code> vs. <code>===</code></h2>




<p>You've probably heard that you should never use <strong>double equals</strong> (loose equality) and just stick to <strong>triple equals</strong> (strict equaility). But following some rules without understanding the reasons behind them is never a good solution to a problem. Let's try to understand how these operators work.</p>




<p><strong>Loose equality</strong> (<strong>==</strong>) compares two values after converting them to <strong>common type</strong>. After conversions (both of the values can be converted) the comparison is performed by strict equality (<strong>===</strong>). So what is a <strong>common type</strong> in this case?</p>




<p>The easiest way to get the idea what happens when using <code>==</code> would be checking the table for conversion rules <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript/Equality_comparisons_and_sameness#Loose_equality_using" target="_blank">here</a> as it's not really something obvious (the details of how conversion works are described later in this article).</p>




<p>So basically this table says that the following expressions will be truthy:</p>


<p><code>js
1 == "1";
"1" == 1;
new String("string") == "string";
1 == { valueOf: function() { return 1; } }; // lulz, it's not a joke ;)
1 == true;
false == 0;
"Fri Jan 01 2016 00:00:00 GMT+0100 (CET)" == new Date(2016, 0, 1)
"1,2" == [1,2] // because why not?
</code></p>

<p>Seems quite "exotic", right? But is <strong>loose equality</strong> actually useful?</p>




<p>Yes, it is. I can imagine 3 scenarios where it comes in handy.</p>




<p>The first scenario would be comparing integers from the forms when you don't really care about strict equality and types:</p>


<p><code>js
if ($('.my-awesome-input').val() == 100) {
  // do something here
}
</code></p>

<p>In such case it may turn out that we don't really care if we compare strings or integers, either <code>"100"</code> and <code>100</code> are fine and we don't need to perform any explicit conversions.</p>




<p>The second use case would be treating both <code>undefined</code> and <code>null</code> as the same thing meaning lack of some value. With strict equality we would need to check for both values:</p>


<p>``` js
x = getSomeValue();</p>

<p>if (x !== undefined &amp;&amp; x !== null) {
  // some logic
}
```</p>

<p>Doesn't look that nice. We could clean it up with loose equality and simply check if something is not <code>null</code>-ish:</p>


<p>``` js
x = getSomeValue();</p>

<p>if (x != null) {
  // some logic
}
```</p>

<p>The last use case would be comparing <strong>primitives</strong> and <strong>objects</strong>. It's especially useful when dealing with both primitive strings (<code>"simple string"</code>) and strings as objects (<code>new String("string as object")</code>:</p>


<p>``` js
x = getSomeValue();</p>

<p>if (x != &ldquo;some special value&rdquo;) {
  // some logic
}
```</p>

<p>With strict equality we would probably need to explicitly convert objects to strings using <code>toString()</code>, which is not that bad, but loose equality looks arguably cleaner.</p>




<h2>Surprise #4 - equality gotcha #1: <code>NaN</code></h2>




<p>Do you know how to identify <strong>NaN</strong> in <strong>JavaScript</strong>. Sounds like a silly question, right? Well, not really, both of the following expressions are falsey:</p>


<p><code>js
NaN == NaN; // =&gt; false
NaN === NaN; // =&gt; false
</code></p>

<p>Fortunately, there is still a way to check for <code>NaN</code>: it is the only value in JS that is not equal to itself:</p>


<p><code>js
NaN != NaN; // =&gt; true
NaN !== NaN; // =&gt; true
</code></p>

<p>You could either take advantage of this behaviour or use <code>isNaN</code> function:</p>


<p><code>js
isNaN(NaN); // =&gt; true
</code></p>

<p>There is one more possibility to test for <code>NaN</code>: <code>Object.is</code> function, which is very similar to <strong>strict equality</strong>, but with few exceptions. One of those is comparing <code>NaN</code> values:</p>


<p><code>js
NaN === NaN // =&gt; false
Object.is(NaN, NaN); // =&gt; true
</code></p>

<h2>Surprise #5 - equality gotcha #2: comparing objects</h2>




<p>There is one more gotcha besides <code>NaN</code> when it comes to testing for equality: <strong>comparing objects</strong>. If you think you can easily compare arrays with the same elements or objects with the same keys and values, you might be quite surprised:</p>


<p><code>js
[1, 2, 3] == [1, 2, 3]; // false
[1, 2, 3] === [1, 2, 3]; // false
{ comparing: "objects" } == { comparing: "objects" }; // false
{ comparing: "objects" } === { comparing: "objects" }; // false
</code></p>

<p>The reason behind it is quite simple though: <strong>strict equality</strong> doesn't compare the values, but identities instead. And two different objects are, well, different, unless they are referring to the exactly same thing.</p>




<p>How about <strong>loose equality</strong>? As already discussed, if the types are the same, the values are compared using <strong>strict equality</strong>. It doesn't work with <code>Object.is</code> either. The only option for objects is to compare each key and associated value with the ones from the other object.</p>




<h2>Surprise #6 - <code>instanceof</code> and <code>typeof</code></h2>




<p>There seems to be a lot of confusion regarding those two and how use them in different contexts. Basically, <code>typeof</code> should be used for getting the basic <strong>JavaScript</strong> type of given <strong>expression</strong> (i.e. undefined, object, boolean, string, number, string, function or symbol) and <strong>instanceof</strong> should be used for checking if a prototype of a given constructor is present in expression's prototype chain. Even if they may seem to be similar at times, they should be used in very different use cases, check the following examples:</p>


<p>``` js
typeof &ldquo;basic string&rdquo;  // => &ldquo;string&rdquo;, it&rsquo;s a primitive so looks good so far
typeof new String(&ldquo;basic string&rdquo; ) // => &ldquo;object&rdquo;, because it&rsquo;s no longer a primitive!</p>

<p>&ldquo;basic string&rdquo; instanceof String // => false, because &ldquo;basic string&rdquo; is a primitive
1 instanceof Number // => false, same reason, 1 is a primitive</p>

<p>[] instanceof Array // => true
[] instanceof Object // => true, array is not a primitive</p>

<p>typeof [] // => &ldquo;object&rdquo;, there is no array primitive, it&rsquo;s still an object
```</p>

<p>Unforunately, it's not that easy in all cases. There are 2 exceptions regarding usage of <code>typeof</code> that are quite surprising.</p>




<p>There is <strong>undefined</strong> type which would be returned for <code>undefined</code> expression, but what about <code>null</code>? Turns out that its type is <strong>object</strong>! There were some attempts to remove this confusion - like this proposal for introducing <a href="http://wiki.ecmascript.org/doku.php?id=harmony:typeof_null" target="_blank">null type</a> - but they were eventually rejected.</p>




<p>And another suprise: <strong>NaN</strong>. What is the type of something that is not a number? Well, it's <strong>number</strong> of course ;). As funny as it sounds, it is in accordance with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IEEE_floating_point" target="_blank">IEEE Standard for Floating-Point Arithmetic</a> and the concept of <code>NaN</code> is kind of number-ish, so this behaviour is somehow justified.</p>




<h2>Surprise #7 - <code>Number.toFixed()</code> returning strings</h2>




<p>Imagine you want to round some number in <strong>JavaScript</strong> and do some math with it. Apparently <code>Math.round()</code> is capable only of rounding to the nearest integer, so we need to find some better solution. There is <code>Number.toFixed()</code> function which seems to do the job. Let's try it out:</p>


<p><code>js
123.789.toFixed(1) + 2 // =&gt; 123.82, huh?
</code></p>

<p>Is math broken in JS? Not really. It's just the fact that <code>Number.toFixed()</code> returns a string, not a numeric type! And its intention is not really to perform rounding for math operations, it's only for formatting! Too bad there is no built-in function to do such simple operation, but if you expect a numeric type, you can just handle it with <code>+</code> <strong>unary prefix operator</strong>, which won't be used as an <strong>addition operator</strong>, but will perform <strong>conversion to number</strong> in such case:</p>


<p><code>js
const number = +123.789.toFixed(1);
number // =&gt; 123.8
</code></p>

<h2>Surprise #8 - Plus (<code>+</code>) operator and results of addition</h2>




<blockquote>"Adding stuff in JavaScript is simple, obvious and not surprising" - No one ever</blockquote>




<p>Have you ever watched <a href="https://www.destroyallsoftware.com/talks/wat" target="_blank">Wat</a> by Gary Bernhardt? If not, I highly encourage you to do it now, it's absolutely hillarious and concerns a lot of "odd" parts of <strong>JavaScript</strong>.</p>




<p>Let's try to explain most of those odd results when using <code>+</code> operator. Beware: once you finishing reading it, you will actually not find most of these results that surprising, it will be just "different". I'm not sure yet if it's a good or a bad thing :).</p>




<p>Take a look at the following examples:</p>


<p><code>js
[] + [] // =&gt; ""
[] + {} // =&gt; "[object Object]"
{} + [] // =&gt; 0 // wut...
{} + {} // =&gt; "[object Object][object Object]"
[] + 1 // =&gt; "1" // it's a string!
[1] + 2 =&gt; // =&gt; "12"
[1, 2] + 2 // =&gt; "1,22"
3 + true // =&gt; 4
new Date(2016, 0 , 1) + 123 // =&gt; "Fri Jan 01 2016 00:00:00 GMT+0100 (CET)123"
({ toString: function() { return "trolololo"; } }) + new Date(2016, 0 , 1) // =&gt; "trolololoFri Jan 01 2016 00:00:00 GMT+0100 (CET)"
1 + { valueOf: function() { return 10; }, toString: function() { return 5; } } // =&gt; 11
1 + { toString: function() { return 10; } } // =&gt; 11
1 + undefined // =&gt; NaN
1 + null // =&gt; 1
</code></p>

<div class="img-center-wrapper">
  <img src="/images/js_results_not_so_wut.jpg" title="js_results_not_so_wut" alt="js_results_not_so_wut">
</div>




<p>All of these results may seem to be somehow exotic, but only one of them, maybe two at most, are exceptional. The basic thing before figuring out the result of those expressions is understanding what is happening under the hood. In <strong>JavaScript</strong> you can only add numbers and strings, all other types must be converted to one of thos before. The <code>+</code> operator basically converts each value to primitive (which are: undefined, null, booleans, numbers and strings). This convertion is handled by the internal operation called <code>ToPrimitive</code> which has the following signature: <code>ToPrimitive(input, PreferredType)</code>. The <code>PreferredType</code> can be either <strong>number</strong> or <strong>string</strong>. The algorithm of this operation is quite simple, here are the steps if <strong>string</strong> is the preferred type:</p>




<ul>
  <li>return <code>input</code> if it's already a primitive</li>
  <li>If it's not a primitive, call <code>toString()</code> method on <code>input</code> and return the result if it's a primitive value</li>
  <li>If it's not a primitive, call <code>valueOf()</code> method on <code>input</code> and return the result if it's a primitive value</li>
  <li>If it's not a primitive, throw <code>TypeError</code></li>
</ul>




<p>For <code>number</code> as preferred type the only difference is the sequence of steps 2 and 3: <code>valueOf</code> method will be called first and if it doesn't return a primitive then <code>toString</code> method wil be called. In most cases <code>number</code> will be the preferred type, <code>string</code> will be used only when dealing with the instances of <code>Date</code>.</p>




<p>Now that we know what is going on under the hood let's explain the results from the examples above.</p>




<p>The result of calling <code>valueOf</code> method on <strong>objects</strong> (<code>{}</code>) and <strong>arrays</strong> (which technically are also objects) is simply the object itself, so it's not a primitive. However, for objects <code>toString()</code> method will return <code>"[object Object]"</code> and for arrays it will return empty string - <code>""</code>. Now we have primitives that can be added. From this point we can predict the results of operation like <code>{} + {}</code>, <code>[] + {}</code> or even:</p>


<p><code>js
1 + { valueOf: function() { return 10; }, toString: function() { return 5; } };
</code></p>

<p>and: </p>


<p><code>
1 + { toString: function() { return 10; } };
</code></p>

<p>If you remember that <string>string</string> is the preferred type for operations involving dates, the result of <code>({ toString: function() { return "surprise!"; } }) + new Date(2016, 0 , 1)</code> is not really surprising anymore. But how is it possible that <code>{} + []</code> returns <code>0</code>, not <code>"[object Object]"</code>?</p>




<p>Most likely <code>{}</code> in the beginning is interpreted as an empty block and it's ignored. You can verify it by putting the empty object inside parentheses (<code>({}) + []</code>), the result will be <code>"[object Object]"</code>. So in fact that expression is interpreted as <code>+[]</code> which is very different from the addition! As I've already mentioned before, it's the <strong>unary prefix operator</strong> which performs conversion to number. For arrays the result of such conversion is simply 0.</p>




<p>And why does <code>1 + undefined</code> return <code>NaN</code>? We can add only numbers and strings, <code>undefined</code> is neither of them, so it must be converted to a number in this case. The result of such operation is simply <code>NaN</code> and <code>1 + NaN</code> is still <code>NaN</code>.</p>




<h2>Surprise #9 - No integers and floats - just numbers</h2>




<p>In most programming languages there are different type of numbers, like integers and floats. What is again surprising about <strong>JavaScript</strong> is that all numbers are simply double precision floating point numbers! This has a huge impact of anything related to math, even for such things like precision. Take a look at the following example:</p>


<p><code>
9999999999999999 === 10000000000000000 // =&gt; true
</code></p>

<p>This is definitely not something that would be expected here. If you are planning to do any serious math in <strong>JavaScript</strong>, make sure you won't run into any issues caused by the implementation of the numbers.</p>




<h2>Wrapping up</h2>




<p><strong>JavaScript</strong> may sometimes seem like it's "broken" somehow, especially comparing to other programming languages. However, many of these features are quite <strong>intentional</strong> and others are consequences of some decisions. There are still few things that seem to be really odd, but after digging deeper they start to make sense (or at least don't look like some voodoo magic), so to avoid unfortunate surprises it's definitely worth learning about those odd parts of <strong>JavaScript</strong>.</p>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ember and ES7: async / await]]></title>
    <link href="https://karolgalanciak.com/blog/2015/12/18/ember-and-es7-async-slash-await/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-18T09:50:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://karolgalanciak.com/blog/2015/12/18/ember-and-es7-async-slash-await</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the <a href="http://karolgalanciak.com/blog/2015/12/02/ember-and-es7-decorators/" target="_blank">previous blog post</a> we were exploring a new wonderful feature coming with ECMAScript 7: decorators. This time we are going to learn about <code>async / await</code>, which is at this moment at Stage 3 in <a href="https://tc39.github.io/process-document/" target="_blank">TC39 process</a>, which means it's already a release candidate that passed Proposal and Draft stages. Just like decorators, it's already available in <a href="https://babeljs.io">Babel</a>. Let's see what kind of benefits does it offer.</p>




<!--more-->




<h2>A little history of writing asynchronous code in JavaScript</h2>




<p>The most basic and only available solution to write asynchronous code until recently was using callbacks. Let's check  example with multiple HTTP requests with fetching some user with id 1 and creating some task list and task for this user assuming that we have <code>HTTPService</code> that performs <code>GET</code> and <code>POST</code> requests:</p>


<p>``` javascript</p>

<p>HTTPService.get(&lsquo;/users/1&rsquo;, functions(user) {
  HTTPService.post(&lsquo;/task_lists&rsquo;, { name: <code>default for ${user.name}</code>, user_id: user.id }, function(taskList) {</p>

<pre><code>HTTPService.post('/tasks', { name: 'finish setup', task_list_id: taskList.id }, function(task) {
  console.log(`created task ${task.id} for user ${user.id}`);
}, function(error) {
  console.log(error);
});
</code></pre>

<p>  }, function(error) {</p>

<pre><code>console.log(error);
</code></pre>

<p>  });
});
}, function(error) {
  console.log(error);
});
```</p>

<p>Well, it's not exactly readable. Every inner function depends on the result from previous function which easily leads to Callback Hell a.k.a. Pyramid of Doom. Adding error handling for every callback makes it even worse. Could we somehow make it linear and more readable?</p>




<p>The answer is yes, thanks to promises. I assume that if you use Ember you already know what they are and how they work as they are pretty common in this framework, but for better undertanding you may want to check the <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/pl/docs/Web/JavaScript/Reference/Global_Objects/Promise" target="_blank">reference</a>. Let's imagine that our <code>HTTPService</code> returns a promise instead of expecting callback-flow. How would the code look in such case?</p>


<p><code>`` javascript
HTTPService.get('/users/1').then(user =&gt; {
  return HTTPService.post('/task_lists', { name: 'default', user_id: user.id });
}).then(taskList =&gt; {
  return HTTPService.post('/tasks', { name: 'finish setup', task_list_id: taskList.id });
}).then(task =&gt; {
  console.log(</code>created task ${task.id} for user ${user.id}`);
}).catch(error => {
  console.log(error);
});</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>Isn't it much cleaner? We made the consecutive function calling linear and simplified error handling by having generic function chained in the end.</p>




<p>But still, something doesn't seem right. Promises make the code much better comparing to callbacks, but the syntax itself is a bit heavy as it's totally different than the standard synchronous code. Is it even possible to write asynchronous code (almost) the same way as a synchronous one? Sure it is! Say hello to your new friend: <code>async / await</code>.</p>




<h2>async / await keywords - what they are how to use them</h2>




<p>Imagine for a moment that <code>HTTPService</code> performs synchronous operations. How different would be a code flow when using it? Let's give it a try:</p>


<p><code>javascript
let user = HTTPService.get('/users/1');
let taskList = HTTPService.post('/task_lists', { name: 'default', user_id: user.id });
let task = HTTPService.post('/tasks', { name: 'finish setup', task_list_id: taskList.id });
console.log(`created task ${task.id} for user ${user.id}`);
</code></p>

<p>What about error handling? We can use <code>try / catch</code> construct to catch any error:</p>


<p><code>javascript
try {
  let user = HTTPService.get('/users/1');
  let taskList = HTTPService.post('/task_lists', { name: 'default', user_id: user.id });
  let task = HTTPService.post('/tasks', { name: 'finish setup', task_list_id: taskList.id });
  console.log(`created task ${task.id} for user ${user.id}`);
} catch (error) {
  console.log(error);
}
</code></p>

<p>The amazing thing is that we can preserve that flow, even though HTTPService returns promises! We just need to <code>await</code> for the result of the asynchronous function call:</p>


<p><code>javascript
try {
  let user = await HTTPService.get('/users/1');
  let taskList = await HTTPService.post('/task_lists', { name: 'default', user_id: user.id });
  let task = await HTTPService.post('/tasks', { name: 'finish setup', task_list_id: taskList.id });
  console.log(`created task ${task.id} for user ${user.id}`);
} catch (error) {
  console.log(error);
}
</code></p>

<p>Compare this code to the first version with Pyramid of Doom or even the <code>then</code> chaining in promises - it looks perfectly natural now. Basically, <code>await</code> is a keyword indicating that we wait for the promise to be fulfilled in this place. What about <code>async</code>? Every function that uses <code>await</code> keyword is <code>async</code> so to make our code actually usable we need to wrap it in such function by using this keyword before its definition:</p>


<p>``` javascript
async function setUpDefaultTask() {
  try {</p>

<pre><code>let user = await HTTPService.get('/users/1');
let taskList = await HTTPService.post('/task_lists', { name: 'default', user_id: user.id });
let task = await HTTPService.post('/tasks', { name: 'finish setup', task_list_id: taskList.id });
console.log(`created task ${task.id} for user ${user.id}`);
</code></pre>

<p>  } catch (error) {</p>

<pre><code>console.log(error);
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}
```</p>

<p>From that moment you probably don't think about coming back to the old way of writing asynchronous code :).</p>




<h2>async / await and Ember</h2>




<p>To start using <code>async / await</code> in your Ember app you just need to include polyfill in <code>ember-cli-build.js</code>:</p>


<p>``` javascript
var EmberApp = require(&lsquo;ember-cli/lib/broccoli/ember-app&rsquo;);</p>

<p>module.exports = function(defaults) {
  var app = new EmberApp({</p>

<pre><code>babel: {
  includePolyfill: true
}
</code></pre>

<p>  });</p>

<p>  return app.toTree();
};
```</p>

<p>Otherwise you will get error with <code>regeneratorRuntime</code> being undefined. You may also consider disabling <code>jshint</code> which sadly doesn't support <code>async / await</code> yet. You might also think about switching to <a href="https://github.com/jonathanKingston/ember-cli-eslint" target="_blank">eslint</a> with <code>babel-esling</code>, which supports every feature implemented in Babel.</p>




<p>Where could it be used? The good canditate would be <code>actions</code> functions in your components / controllers where you probably have a lot of promises with some API calls. Imagine that you have some action with creating a task and transitioning to the <code>task</code> route. With <code>async / await</code> you could simply write it like that:</p>


<p>``` javascript
import Ember from &lsquo;ember&rsquo;;</p>

<p>export default Ember.Controller.extend({
  actions: {</p>

<pre><code>async save() {
  let task = await this.get('task').save();
  this.transitionToRoute('tasks.show', task);
}
</code></pre>

<p>  }
});
```</p>

<p>Which is much simpler than using <code>then</code>:</p>


<p>``` javascript
import Ember from &lsquo;ember&rsquo;;</p>

<p>export default Ember.Controller.extend({
  actions: {</p>

<pre><code>save() {
  this.get('task').save().then(() =&gt; {
    this.transitionToRoute('tasks.show', task);
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>  }
});
```</p>

<p>The other usecase would be acceptance tests. I always forget about using <code>andThen</code> when writing new tests and get failures in something that looks as a valid test. If that's also a case with you then switching to <code>async / await</code> will solve that problem forever. Here's a little example with using traditional approach with <code>andThen</code>:</p>


<p>``` javascript
import Ember from &lsquo;ember&rsquo;;
import {
  module,
  test
} from &lsquo;qunit&rsquo;;</p>

<p>var application;</p>

<p>module(&lsquo;Acceptance: SomeTest&rsquo;, {
  beforeEach: function() {</p>

<pre><code>application = startApp();
</code></pre>

<p>  },</p>

<p>  afterEach: function() {</p>

<pre><code>Ember.run(application, 'destroy');
</code></pre>

<p>  }
});</p>

<p>test(&lsquo;it clicks button&rsquo;, function(assert) {
  click(&lsquo;.some-button&rsquo;);</p>

<p>  andThen(function()  {</p>

<pre><code>assert.equal(find('.clicked-button').length, 1);
</code></pre>

<p>  });
});
```</p>

<p>Not really ideal. The example below looks much better:</p>


<p>``` javascript
import Ember from &lsquo;ember&rsquo;;
import {
  module,
  test
} from &lsquo;qunit&rsquo;;</p>

<p>var application;</p>

<p>module(&lsquo;Acceptance: SomeTest&rsquo;, {
  beforeEach: function() {</p>

<pre><code>application = startApp();
</code></pre>

<p>  },</p>

<p>  afterEach: function() {</p>

<pre><code>Ember.run(application, 'destroy');
</code></pre>

<p>  }
});</p>

<p>test(&lsquo;it clicks button&rsquo;, async function(assert) {
  await click(&lsquo;.some-button&rsquo;);
  assert.equal(find(&lsquo;.clicked-button&rsquo;).length, 1);
});
```</p>

<p>Much more intuitive, we just need to remember about adding <code>async</code> before callback in <code>test</code> function, but we are going to get syntax error if we use <code>await</code> in not <code>async</code> function, so the issue will be obvious.</p>




<h2>Wrapping up</h2>




<p><code>async / await</code> is another excellent addition in Javascript world, which may become a real game changer when it comes to writing asynchronous code. Thanks to Babel again, we can easily start using it even today.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
